Kabeh Vaziri Soyeb Barot Gartner agentic
AI workforce CIO Kabeh Vaziri Soyeb Barot
Gartner agentic AI workforce
CIO
Hello and welcome to this Gartner webinar
How to create a workforce that can keep up
with AI Your task is driving a stronger
performance on your organization's
missioncritical priorities To do that you
need trusted guidance that provides
clarity not just information
At Gartner we deliver that clarity by
combining forwardlooking insights from our
2400 experts with rigorous proprietary
research methodologies Our perspective is
uniquely informed by our handson work with
50010000 client interactions across every
major function geography industry and
sector We don't just provide the business
and technology insights We work with you
to apply them equipping your team with
practical tools and expert guidance to
achieve your goals So whether you're new
to Gartner or one of our existing clients
today you'll get actionable objective
insights rooted in human intelligence to
help you move forward with confidence I'm
Sneha Bhar your moderator for this session
Before we get started I have a few tips to
help enhance your webinar experience
Here are our rules of engagement for
watching this session We'll pause for a
moment to give you time to review them
Around the video player you'll find a
variety of ways to interact with the
session We encourage you to participate by
adding in your questions and thoughts in
the Ask the Speaker box You can either
submit a question anonymously or if you
choose your name title and company can be
visible along with your question
Navigate to the bottom of the page to
download additional resources And
throughout the program you can rate the
session and share feedback To submit your
rating locate the rate session link below
the player A box will open for you to
select one to five hearts Please note that
five hearts is the top rating Tell your
feedback on the insights provided in the
leave further feedback box and click send
This webinar is being recorded You can
watch this presentation again and find
more great insights on demand at
gardnercomwebinars
Now I'd like to welcome Gartner Managing
Vice President Kabeh Vaziri and
Distinguished Vice President Analyst Soeb
Barot Kabeh and Soeb thanks for joining us
today And now I'll turn it over to you
Thank you Sneha Pleasure to be here And hi
everyone on the line This is an important
topic and it's a topic that Soeb and I
have put our heart into it You know for
all of the past year I'm very happy to be
bringing this to you Let's move to the
next page Sneha
Actually I can do that
So let me show you some of the information
on this topic that I think you know is
really relevant I really like by starting
with data After all you know we have our
own unique proprietary data and I think it
has a great story
There is a lot of AI everywhere right You
know some organizations are sprinkling it
on the workflows and some places you know
we are seeing more methodical approaches
But regardless it's really feeling like
it's everywhere
If you start from the left you can see
that 24 of the organizations have scaled
AI in multiple business units
And that we are expecting that the
proportion of the work done by AI agents
to really you know significantly increase
over the next three years
All of this is really causing AI to get to
the core of the work right So a lot of
us within our daily jobs might feel like
you know there are agents that might help
us with you know assisting or querying or
analyzing simple tasks
At the same time if you look at the middle
all of this is causing two things So as as
all of that is happening there are
backgrounds that are more unique
backgrounds that are more combined
synthesized backgrounds that are becoming
more and more attractive to CIOs and
executives across the board right So it's
no longer this one person with this unique
expertise with this one domain knowledge
It's a person who's combining multiple
things So a lot of organizations are
finding it hard to figure out you know
what talent they need and who to bring in
even if there are a lot of talented people
inside So that understanding is hard And
also because AI is taking over some of the
routine tasks analyzing etc
The premium on innovation and
problemsolving skills or is increasing
right So when in our recent survey of the
CIOs and top executive leaders we found
that the top two critical skills for IT
staff was actually innovation and
problemsolving If you don't have them that
might create a roadblock in terms of you
know realizing your outcomes
And then on the right side the talent
pipeline is broken Well you know more than
half of enterprises are focusing on
augmenting not replacing employees And
forty percent of enterprises have no
strategy Well forty percent have a
strategy in place for skills atrophy but
that means sixty percent don't right And
as you know if you don't use a skill you
might just lose it And so this is really
important as AI taking is taking over
tasks and you know critical capabilities
You know how do we think about ourselves
as humans and our powers and you know
superpowers
I want to orient you to another data point
here because I know that jobs are all over
the news and everyone thinks about it You
know either for your organizations or even
I think deeply personal right Like you
know everyone I think feels um some of
that anxiety
So across 2025 we looked at 14 million AI
layoff data points We analyzed them for AI
and we found that only less than 1 of them
are about AI productivity There are a lot
of reasons for layoffs of course but you
know AI productivity was not the one that
you know drove the number to be as high as
14 million
A lot of what's happening is that AI is
not causing necessarily a substitution for
humansnot a layoff story but a lot of
chaos right And by chaos I mean it's not
necessarily just job loss it's also a lot
of rapid evolution of the existing jobs
It's not that some people will not lose
their jobs but it's also that a lot of
people will see their jobs changing We
might see new jobs created and we will see
a lot of jobs morphing
And so this chaos is where we will need to
pay attention and
you know have this conversation today
And the workforce conversation which is
you know if you think about AI impact on
workforce chaos that we were just talking
about that's not just one conversation
it's really three conversations And and
it's helpful to put it as three
conversations because I think part of what
makes it really difficult is that you will
have one conversation but the person that
you're speaking with they might be having
the other conversation with you right So
starting from the left the first
conversation around AI the executive
conversation is around capacity
reallocation
Is it helping us do more of what matters
Or is it just making us busier
Across the board I speak with a lot of
organizations and I can tell you the
sentiment is our people feel so busy but
we can't really tell what they're busy
with And you know why is it that we feel
like we are increasing personal
productivity but everyone feels so busy
right Like so you know yes AI is creating
some capacity in there but what are we
doing with it Are we able to convert it to
something that you know is is different
The emotional adaptation is real right
Because as I was just talking about that
this chaos Creates a roller coaster for
everyone you know from everyone on the
ground all the way to the penthouse of the
organization and the executives personally
right So the idea would be Will AI
be the force that is going to fracture the
organization or is it going to be
mobilizing it
And work redesign
Is about can we create new value that was
not there before Will AI allow us to do
something that we could not do before
Could we become something that we could
not be before Right
And the thing is these three are very
interdependent If you look at the gray
boxes underneath they all depend on each
other If you don't have people who are
emotionally engaged they're not going to
be creating capacity for you
If you can't create capacity you are not
going to be able to do the work redesign
Right and so they are all very
interdependent which actually adds to the
complexity of having this workforce
conversation and you know what happens as
a result of AI
And when you think of these as
interdependent conversations I think
Across the board what I've observed is
that everyone's first instinct is to focus
on capacity as a first measurable win
because it's very easy to say We put AI
here we are going to save minutes and
hours on this particular job It's a check
the box right
But your first visible win should be with
your people right Bringing them along on
that journey with you so that they feel
ownership of you know what's going to
happen They are part of that
experimentation and innovation with you
and that instead of worrying about their
jobs they are actually excited to become
and like have the jobs of tomorrow and you
know do the kinds of things that you could
not do before
Once you convert those first two to work
redesign and intentional job redesign
that's actually what's going to be the
most durable way of thinking about all of
this right So all three are important You
will probably feel the pressure at
different points in terms of your
workforce planning journey but you know
what you really want is to be very
intentional about you know what is it that
you're trying to win at what point and you
know what are you going to do with that
Now let's let's double click on capacity
reallocation And as usual I think with
with all of our insights we try to make
them as actionable as possible right And
so for the purposes of this conversation
Soeb and I thought well what's the best
way of talking about how to create
capacity Than to talk about a specific job
right Like as a case in point And then
we'll pull up and have the conversations
and insights for you at the workforce
level of course But we thought that
actually it's much easier and much more
tangible if we talk about a specific job
At Gartner we've actually done the
analysis for all of the jobs on the left
and more So you know we have some 20 plus
jobs in IT that we've analyzed We've
started doing some business jobs across HR
and other functions
And the way that we thought about a job on
the right side is actually pretty much a
realworld view of the job because as you
all know jobs can be notoriously different
at different organizations right You can
have the same job with different job
descriptions to different companies You
have years of experience You have even the
same job within the same company It could
be a software engineer who's sitting in
internal IT or a software engineer who's
sitting on the trading floor of the
business right
So the way that we thought of creating a
shared language around it was a capability
This is important because this is going to
set the stage for for the rest of how you
are going to be looking at a particular
job So let me take my time and explain
what I mean
The core capabilities of the job are the
capabilities the set of skills and tasks
that are always owned by this job no
matter what So it doesn't matter whether
you have 10 years of experience or 15 or 3
It doesn't matter where you sit or the
type of an organization At most
organizations if you are a software
engineer you own these particular skills
For example if you are a data scientist
this is always a part of your job
The contextual capabilities would be the
set of capabilities that depend on the
conditions right So that the way that your
team is set up how much trust you
personally have and like you know how
senior you might be the business context
So those are those set of capabilities
So maybe you own them maybe you don't own
them And regardless of our jobs all of us
contribute to a set of shared capabilities
for the organization right So and and
those shared set of capabilities would be
different for different jobs But for any
set of any job that we analyze we actually
look at how this job will contribute to
shared capabilities and shared outcomes
Now with that let me pass it on to Soyeb
who's gonna take you through the same
journey for data scientists
Kabeh thank you so much and it's been an
absolute pleasure as well as a fantastic
collaborating with you and the team trying
to put together the impact on the roles
and how we see these roles being impacted
or redesigned as part of the future of IT
twenty thirty So as organizations try and
actually look into that they're looking at
what that particular org structure is
going to look like how the roles are going
to evolve and what is it that they can do
in order to upscale their talent
Reorganize their teams and also create
pathways as part of what that new
operating model is going to look like in
twenty thirty Now as you can
compare as you can mention for the
purposes of this particular recognition we
are going to focus on the data scientist
role because when we take a look at this
it provides a framework or a blueprint
Because if we take a look at it this
pattern isn't unique and it can be much
more of a repeatable process across the
enterprise for all of the different other
roles that we that we've already gone
through the analysis as well This is what
it's come out Now if we were to focus
specifically on the role of the data
scientist the important insights over here
is more around jobs very significantly
based on context as well
Things around organization structure
technical maturity domain knowledge and
all shape how those particular
capabilities evolve Built from the core
capabilities around problem framing to
data preparation and hypothesis testing
which is what is core to and fundamental
to the job of a data scientist to having
that particular contextual awareness of
what particular kind of features are
really important for a given model in a
domain It would be very different for an
insurance organization versus a supply
chain So having that particular contextual
awareness of what particular features
really matter as part of building those
particular models is something that is
really important
In addition how do you go about that The
deployment strategy so the model
deployment piece the ethics and the
responsible AI piece but also a shared set
of capabilities which is much more around
the research and the innovation the
tooling evaluation itself But more
importantly how do you actually do that
crossfunctional collaboration Because Gone
are the days when you know a data
scientist would just go across and build a
model and then say Okay I'm going to just
throw it off the fence and then that's my
engineering team that needs to take care
of No you need to work in collaboration to
be able to go across and do that And these
are some of the things that these
capabilities which are core to that of a
data scientist
This also means that when you're trying to
redesign that little job it's not one size
fits all It must be contextually and
capability driven
and this is where the workflow comes
across
We can't redesign the job of a data
scientist There's already a debate or an
argument being said that data scientist
was like one of the most coolest jobs back
in 2015 2018 with the rise of machine
learning and hyper around it It still is
but do we see data scientists kind of
moving a lot more towards becoming AI
engineers or AI architects or maybe model
orchestrators in the future
But you can't completely redesign that
without taking into consideration what
does that particular workflow of the human
responsibilities look like within the data
science or machine learning or AI practice
within your organization You have to take
into consideration where the human
elements come in where it's much more the
role is much more static disconnected
assistant and where AI can actually help
in try and augment it or embedded more as
an enabler where AI agents or suggest that
particular code as well as even the
algorithms from a visualization
perspective which would help data
scientists move from a story telling
perspective
Some might actually bucket this and saying
that's a much more of a cautious approach
or a very AI cautious approach in terms of
the redesigning of that job
The second part is where there could be
certain taskspecific automation where data
scientists oversee interpret those
critical results and then guide those
critical problem framing and the model
choices But agentic tools can autonomously
execute a set of welldesigned tasks along
with those critical features that
they need to engineer as part of training
the models building the LLMs or even the
deploying of finetuned models of small
language models out of there And that's
where the operational collaboration comes
in as well because it goes spans
everything from taking into consideration
the data ingestion part but also
monitoring the model once it's deployed in
production to make sure that it's still
working within the expected thresholds and
there is not a significant amount of model
drift and then surfacing those insights as
well
Or else you could go completely AIfirst
where you have a series of interoperable
agents coordinating across multiple
platforms and the data scientists provide
much more of that particular highlevel
oversight set those particular ethical
guardrails and steer that particular
innovation and really push the boundaries
when it comes to thinking outside the box
where most of those particular
orchestration components get automated
using AI
It's it's kind of like as AI matures it
takes over more of that physical execution
and then humans move toward judgment
orchestration and then strategy And this
shift is really critical because we are
thinking about not eliminating the work
we are changing who does what as part of
that bigger process
Now use a particular heat map
This heat map in a way kind of like
reflects where AI affects different
capabilities depending on those particular
workflows
Some tasks become highly automatable
others remain deeply humancentric But
here's the mistake that most organizations
make
They're stopping at automation of looking
at AI just as an automation tool
And if you think about it that way if we
only shrink the jobs based on that we
definitely get efficiency but not growth
because that's where the human centric
piece comes across And the biggest
opportunity that we have is expanding the
typical human work into higher value areas
to what AI kind of takes over
Now with that Kabeh I'll pass it on back
to you in terms of highlighting how how we
redistribute that particular capacity
Absolutely and I want to remind everyone
on the line that any place where you see
data scientist on the page we have done
the analysis for you know 20 some jobs in
IT and some jobs on the business side as
well So definitely take advantage of that
Looking at that heat map that Soyeb Barot
is showing you it's easy to think that you
know okay so you know the colors are going
from you know dark blue to light you know
lighter colors and therefore you know a
lot of it is going gonna go to AI There
is a lot of you know the subtle interplay
in the background right I want to orient
you to to this page which is think about
the X axis being time a factor of time You
know you go from early state of automation
to you know what your new steady state the
desired state might be like let's say in
your S you know whether you want to be AI
first Um at L four L five or maybe you
you you you stay somewhere in the middle
Um and so three things are happening right
So the dark dot the the dark dotted line
is the humans doing less from the jobs
that they have today and that might happen
because AI can do more and more of the
jobs that we have today Again this is not
um a future looking
Page necessarily right Like so this is of
the job descriptions of the capabilities
that we had today You know how might the
relationship the proportion of the job
that used to be done by humans you know go
to AI right So at some level you have AI
doing more of the job Humans doing less of
the job and that differential could be the
capacity that you're creating However a
lot of organizations are reporting that as
all of that is happening there is also a
surge of unplanned work
Some of it for example could be you know
frictions on handoffs and you know people
not knowing where to go Some of it is
frankly AI slop that you know gets created
But also a really really important part of
this is as you are changing the workflows
a lot of organizations start changing
workflows from a place of elimination
Right You know how do we remove tasks How
do we remove handoffs You know how do we
resequence things And when that happens
you are putting a lot of faith in the
escalation process And I'll tell you what
I heard from a CIO just last week They
said You know we've done all these
productivity improvements It takes only
one escalation to wipe out you know a
whole bunch of benefits that we thought we
had harvested from AI That's this
unplanned work and it's not something that
you know at least easily measurable in the
beginning And so the fragile capacity that
you think you might have created because
you know AI is doing more and humans are
doing less of the existing jobs there is
also this unplanned work that happens And
what I want to I guess what I want you
to take away from this page is that the
slope of the three graphs in here That's
entirely up to you as you're developing AI
as you're thinking about how to use it who
to give it to the speed by which all of
this is happening the relationship of the
three signals with each other That's a
design decision right So you know
depending on how you organize these lines
how the lines look like for a particular
job a particular function You'll see
different relationships between these
three signals of capacity and there is
that messy middle Where capacity can feel
very fragile people feel busy but it's not
necessarily good busy right And like the
busyness a lot of it comes from the extra
unplanned work that we didn't know and
also maybe we don't even find valuable
right So so that's that's the three
signals for capacity that I wanted to take
in mind Across the rest of this webinar
we're going to add more signals into it So
we'll go through emotional adaptation
we'll go through work redesign and then
the picture starts you know forming and
building on to each other
Let me
actually
talk to you about the emotional adaptation
a little bit putting the human in the
picture right So as all of that is
happening AI does more humans do less You
know there is the onplant surge There is a
real person There is this data scientist
that we just talked about who's going
through a roller coaster of emotions
They probably started with You know good
faith curiosity caution This sounds
amazing It helps me dig up you know
sketches and diagrams and let me figure
out what I can do with it
Then this person probably experiences
increased productivity some pride right
Like the kind of a thing that used to take
me this long it's taking me less time But
also a little bit of a fear of missing out
because everybody else seems to be getting
more out of it What am I doing wrong Like
so it's a little bit of a mixed bag of
emotions in there
And from there you start thinking about
well this AI thing sounds really good It's
actually getting really good But if it can
do this part of my job really well what
happens to the rest of my job Right So you
know
fluid boundaries blurry boundaries concern
for futurethat's a real thing
And then at some point there is a new
identity new steady state that some will
make it some might not make it You know
some of it depends on the kind of a person
that you are and your aspirations You know
does this new way of working new type of a
job is that useful or not And some of it
is skills right So you know and both of
those things have to come together so that
you know one would make it from early days
of automation to new identity
And the way that I would show that to you
on that same graph that we just looked at
is
it almost looks like a line that has a dip
in the middle right So you know you start
happy and you know wanting to go ahead and
like wanting to try this new thing Reality
kind of kicks in in that messy middle
where you start thinking about well if it
can't do this part of my job well can it
do all of my job
The thing that I want you to think about
is that it's not a given that this
emotional adaptation line is going to go
back up
It is real that there will be some job
loss for some jobs and for some people it
will go down
But it is up to the executives to bring it
back up and I'm going to repeat this again
not just for important jobs but also for
people who have the ability to learn and
on learn and reinvent themselves Right so
it's not just about the single job that
might go away You want to think about this
you know from a job perspective but also
the people that we have that are really
valuable to us And you know Soyeb will go
a little bit more into this as well But
but we definitely think that there there
is like the two of those angles and it is
up to um up to us to make that decision
Again like you know we have agency around
how we want to um look at these signals
and how we want to interpret them
Um and let me take you through this one
more page and then I'll pass it off to
Soyeb But um as you are thinking about
this data scientist in the context of the
job that is changing you know that heat
map a lot of it is going to AI Um
as Soyeb was saying you know uh there
might be different set of non technical
skills that are becoming even more
important now right Or or or not
completely technical skills We wanted to
take a look at how the team element of all
of this might look like right So the team
elements would be who's doing the work how
they're doing the work and what is the
thing that needs to be done right
So for who's doing the work like you know
think of it as um You know these data
scientists are becoming even more domain
experts You know they are bringing
business acumen into the work that they
are doing They are doing a lot more
translation They are shifting fluidly
between the different boundaries different
teams and you know making outcome oriented
decisions and you know orienting everyone
through the the job that needs to be done
The teams are smaller They're
multidisciplinary You can think of it as
you know they come together to fix a
business problem and then they dispatch A
lot of what used to be repetitive work
repetitive analysis
you know data science tasks Can go to AI
which means that there will be more
capacity for a single data scientist to
supervise guide and refine models and
focus on you know complex
creative ethical challenges
But that also means that this this has to
be the person that enjoys that type of
work And in terms of the jobs to be done
well strategic AI leadership domain
integrated analysis those are really the
two that you know we see in terms of you
know how the job itself might be evolving
But Soyeb I'm sure has a lot more
insightful you know double clicks on this
that he can give you So
Kabeh thank you so much And one key
important thing that you kind of mentioned
which I want to just reemphasize is this
particular part of
you have to take the individual into
consideration who are willing to unlearn
learn and reinvent themselves I think
that's so critical because you don't want
To lose as part of that particular atrophy
piece you don't want to lose that
particular domain expertise that
institutional knowledge
And you want to focus on the talent and
the group of individuals who are ready to
you know be agile and ready to learn
something new and completely reinvent
themselves as part of what the future of
in the agentic era or the AI era looks
like
So just doubleclicking on this particular
part of specifically for the data
scientist as you very rightly pointed out
the role evolves into becoming a lot more
hybrid
The data scientist job kind of evolves to
becoming much more strategic domain
specific going beyond just being you know
understanding the math and the algorithm
more from a technical execution to
becoming much more strategic But also even
advisory in terms of what kind of patterns
do they see and what kind of solutions can
help really drive innovation as well as
new opportunities to scale that bigger
business So in a way the data scientists
will need to kind of blend analytical
capabilities alongside developing that
particular business acumen but also think
about it much more from a productcentric
perspective as they build or partner with
business alongside the rest of the
technology groups as well
I mean we are already seeing the data
scientists' roles evolve To becoming much
more AI business partners or product
strategists in terms of building those
particular products in the form of agents
these particular days but then also
becoming domain AI leaders within those
particular industries as well
And that's where the most valuable talent
is around the part where you are able to
actually combine the technical skills but
also bring in the business acumen and
alongside the right AI judgment that would
be required as well for these particular
roles
Now this brings us to a very interesting
graphic which to be very honest raises a
lot of questions And people try and you
know peel the onion as I like to call it
and want to take a look at each of those
peel layers very closely and examine those
peel layers very closely Now let me just
you know set the stage a little bit On the
left what you have are risky skills for
atrophy as well as acceptable skills for
atrophy and on the right you have skills
that are very foundational enduring but
also the new emerging skills as part of
the role for data scientists And it was
very interesting for us to go through this
bigger exercise when we explored other
roles as well as part of that evolution
Now if you take a look at it the human
foundation piece which is where the
analytical curiosity the ethical reasoning
part having that business acumen the
storytelling of that particular data is
something that is core foundational to
that of the data scientists A few other
enduring skills are much more around the
hypothesis formulation the model selection
knowing which particular models would work
best what are those particular feature
variables to be taken into consideration
how do you do experimentation with some
designs and then how do you extend that
particular experimentation and bring it
into your first MVP or scale these
particular models as well
But also the part of like what are some of
those new and emerging skills with AI
agents The governance the responsible AI
governance of it How do you how do you
integrate this cross functionally across
the various applications and this is where
the next generation skills required by
data scientists would be to better
understand about multi agent architectures
How do you design those What kind of
levels of autonomy or semi autonomous
workflows that you can create based on
that Understanding where those particular
business opportunities would be which is
where you identify and say What particular
components do I kind of containerize and
build an agent around which can be used
across multiple use cases Whereas say
trying to build just one monolithic model
as part of it
But as part of this there is Kabeh
highlighted that there is this risk of
losing certain skills because now you're
leaning a
lot more on AI to help with Like do I
now need to not remember spellings anymore
because it will auto correct when I'm
typing my emails Now is that a skill which
is risky for me to lose versus an
acceptable one And that's where for a data
scientist it's more about
The risky skills that they want to make
sure that they safeguard is around the
data interpretation part the storytelling
because that's core that's human that
that's human foundation of what they bring
in the model validation whether it's the
right model or not to be able to challenge
and say that AI can't provide the right
model and the analysis and be able to
break down that analysis But certain
skills Could be acceptable in things like
the routine data cleaning part I've had
data scientists in my team that spend
close to about 30 of their time just data
preparation If that can be automated by AI
I'm more than happy for my data scientists
to not understand fundamentals of data
integration right But that's a skill that
they can lose
Standardization of statistical analysis or
basic visualization generation Where
should I create a Bayesian graph or a
Bayesian plot or should I create a pie
chart Because I'm now speaking with sales
and sales will not understand Bayesian
plots but for them it will be much more
you know bar charts or line graphs Those
particular things it's okay if the data
scientists are losing those skills But
there are a few ones that you want to make
sure that they kind of like hold on to
And this brings us to this particular part
of how do you then redesign that workforce
And this is where the third battle comes
in The third battle is more about how do
you go about redesigning that workforce
Now once AI frees that particular capacity
we need to identify what or define what
humans do next And this cannot be about oh
let's address all of that kind of backlog
that's been sitting there for the past
three years or which we've not been able
to address But it should be something that
is new inspiring value creating for the
business and that's where we need to kind
of fly move in
The way to look at that is how do we
break it down Let's break it down in an
analytical fashion Right
What are some of the things that are
routine
That AI will automate or we should
leverage AI to automate
coordination like handoff like handoff
that need to happen between the the
various systems Now AI can definitely help
accelerate it right But sense making like
analyzing it as well as looking for
opportunities from an innovation
perspective And that's where you know AI
can help bolster humans taking that
particular idea and then formulating it
even more
But then more important is the connections
building those particular relationships
having that particular deeper
understanding of the business in the
industry
That AI will multiply
And you could use this as a way to kind
of see as to how the work gets impacted
The human work kind of like falls into
these categories that we listed out But AI
could automate most of those particular
routine or enhancing that particular
coordination or support that particular
sense making But this framework can really
help redesign what that particular feature
of your CIO Now In order to bring that
into perspective from a data scientist
perspective
here's what it would look like You have
the AI assisted development norm which is
where AI driven tools can automate data
exploration identifying of feature
variables and the feature engineering part
And also in most cases which we've seen
with auto ML tools about model selection
where I don't even need to know which
particular model will be best the system
actually identifies it So that's where
that assisted automated piece comes across
But also around the part of like where do
you you know the ownership boundaries kind
of blur on data scientists increasingly
measured by business outcomes more than
the kind of models that they actually
create It's not just about the accuracy of
the model itself but the impact that you
have I've been in discussions where I've
had a data scientist defending and saying
My the models providing ninety percent and
ninety eight percent accuracy but the
business sitting over there and saying Oh
but that's not helped with customer
attrition or move that particular needle
by even five percent or two percent which
is what they were expecting So you could
have a really good Model but if it doesn't
have that particular business outcome or
business impact you could have one of the
best models with the highest amount of
accuracy but it's not really helping move
that particular dial when it comes to
customer retention or growth
But it also kind of moves from shifting
towards more becoming product centric
outcomes as well Collaborating with the
various patterns or different business
units
building that particular platform from a
resiliency perspective that can be
leveraged across various lines of business
within the organization But more
importantly the ability to be able to
quickly do prototypes iterate and then go
out of that I've seen organizations where
they would say that their data scientists
were able to prototype something in a
matter of over a weekend and they would
have a model ready by Monday But then it
takes them almost about three months to
get that particular model into production
and integrated within their production
environment as part of that workflow So
those are where these particular roles and
the collaboration becomes quite important
as part of
it as well Now
moving along
one of the things that we need to think
about is
Is this much more specific to the data
scientist itself or what does that
particular impact really look at for all
of the roles across DNA
So let's zoom out a bit and see as to
how would you go about redesigning that
particular workforce when the AI future
state is unknown
Based on our analysis this is what the
data analytics IT 2030 impact looks like
What particular you know how do you how do
you
make data available or govern the data
much better
Engineer that particular data predict and
optimize it enable the value and decide
and act on that particular data
What are those particular levels or the
percentage of FTS that are going to be
impacted
Areas where we are going to see an
increase in the headcount
Being stable and requiring significant
amount of rescaling that would be there
But I want everybody to take a step back a
little bit and just observe this
If you take a look at it this was not
specific to the role of a data scientist a
data engineer a data product manager None
of those roles that we identify within DNI
but it is focused on how does the workflow
actually change It's more about learning
how do you make data available how do you
engineer data better or deliver it in the
form of probably data products in a
combination of a fabric and a mesh
or how do you make sure that you are
enabling value by building models on top
of those bigger data products that make it
much more easier to derive insights
And the roles as we discussed and Kabeh
mentioned also the roles could shift and
change The responsibilities in the
workflow is where you need to tie that
down
So
Let's take a look at what does that IT
workforce
look like and especially more from a
journey perspective for the individual
roles So if we take a look at and I
want to frame it in this particular
In this particular framework of saying
with these particular jobs that are there
for the data foundation we saw that
particular onion with the human foundation
piece What roles are core and portable But
then what does that particular future
archetype actually look like
Now with that being said if we take a look
at what that particular evolution for a
data scientist looks like
the data scientist if they envision
themselves Or if you are redesigning that
particular workforce for your data
scientists to becoming much more like
platform builders some of the core
capabilities that would be really required
as part of becoming platform builders
would be having a deeper understanding of
agent orchestration
Having a deeper understanding of AI
engineering or at least the foundational
aspects of AI engineering from a model ops
perspective or Gen AI ops or even agent
dev ops as part of it
But in addition the portable shared
capabilities around understanding of
prompt engineering the crossdomain
integration between various applications
that are there as part of it But also
what's going to be unique to the platform
builders role is a deeper understanding of
AI infrastructure
The understanding of how do you do APIs
and microservices management
DevOps and CICD as well as the AI
orchestration piece as well
Now what this helps you do is on one
particular side work with talent work with
your data scientists and say where do you
see yourself three years from now or five
years from now As part of your evolution
in an agentic AI era or an AI era in
the future and what is that particular
skill set or upskilling path that you can
create and the kind of capabilities that
they need to upskill on to be platform
builders or even compliance champions or
translators
Now you might say that this is a very this
is much more of a a simpler path for a
data scientist coming from that particular
domain of data science and understanding
of data analytics
But this also gives an opportunity for
going cross domain as well So now imagine
you have a SOC analyst
Who has aspirations of becoming a data
analytics compliance champion
and quite frankly they have a significant
amount of understanding of data analytics
They understand security monitoring they
understand governance risk compliance and
some of that particular ethical AI data
oversight that is there as well
So for them for a saw analyst to go in
this particular path of becoming a data
and analytics compliance champion context
engineering and AI governance would be
core But then some of those particular
shared portable ones which I'm sure we all
are now much better prompt engineers than
we were at least about 18 months ago but
they will need to have a deeper
understanding of how do you manage data
what kind of data platforms exist and how
do you manage structured semi structured
and structured content and how does that
get managed within a data management
portfolio
But then there are certain things that are
very unique to a compliance a data
analytics compliance champion It is much
more about a deeper understanding of data
audit and compliance postures
What are those particular frameworks How
do you go about governing stewarding that
particular data Understanding of policy
management and the regulations and how do
you enforce those particular policies that
are there as well But in addition to that
also how do you go about managing the risk
with the AI models that are there as well
So this definitely creates that particular
path for AI
for a saw catalyst to You know switch
lanes and then become data compliance
champions taking some of those particular
core skills that they already have but
upskilling in specific areas as a way to
shift careers as well
Now let me pass it on back to Kabeh to
bring us home with this
So interesting you know going from a SOC
analyst to a DNA compliance champion I
want to bring us home by bringing the
signals together right So if you remember
in this first section we talked about
capacity reallocation and the three
workforce signals that you would track
right So AI does more
humans do less and there is a surge in
unplanned demand
Then we also talked about the emotional
adaptation The line goes down before you
choose to bring it up Right so that's the
goldcolored line
The third line which Soya was just talking
about is new value and new work that
you're going to be creating by redesigning
jobs by rethinking the career paths by
rethinking you know the jobs that need to
be done
And the messy middle in the middle is the
transition phase where AI has started
releasing capacity The organization has
the opportunity to convert it into new
value and this is where all three of these
sections come together around capacity
emotional adaptation and work redesign so
that you can have the five signals that
you can track to figure out where your
workforce actually is and what you need to
do so that you can unlock the next level
of maturity for workforce transformation
in this AI journey And this is not
something that any one organization or any
one function can do together So for the
final slide here I just wanted to orient
you towards that this is really a
threesided transformation right So you
have capacity reallocation
where well
you want the CIOs to provide the capacity
potential as the owners or the stewards of
technology but they have to work with the
CHRs to create readiness They have to work
with the CFO to understand constraints On
the emotional adaptation side you have the
CIO and the business leaders building
trust whereas you know the CHR might be
thinking about how do I manage their
skepticism and fear and you know help them
go through that And in work redesign same
thing you know the CIO and the CHR and the
business leads will have to all work
together
And to bring it like totally back home at
the bottom of the page if you remember we
started from a place of these are three
independent battles When it goes wrong
everything goes wrong But also when it
goes well everything goes well So best of
luck to you in this threesided
transformation And really great to be
spending the hour with you If you have any
questions we are happy to take them
And Kabeh I see a list of questions One of
the questions that I want to address very
quickly right now itself which was more
about Do we have access to those
particular analysis On the previous page
we did see the links to those particular
research notes But in addition if you have
your Gartner subscription there is a micro
site that lists out all of the
analysis that we've done for the
individual jobs That we discussed but we
are adding other business functional
domains as well HR in one of them and then
there are others that are coming So you do
have access through your Gartner
subscription to all of these critical
analysis for the individual jobs and roles
Now
in terms of the questions how about we
begin with
This one um was the 14 million jobs lost
across all industries Um this was like
they just curious about uh
that particular survey data Yeah I can
take that one Yes it is cross industries
Um you know we've looked at it across
industries and we looked at you know what
percentage of them are AI layoffs data
There are a couple of indepth notes that
you know we can share as part of the
follow up for this call Okay
great thank you
There's one other question that came up
which caught my attention and I think it's
being framed fantastically that this is
the first time that we have close to about
five to six generations working together
and they have different approaches to how
dealing with the understanding of AI but
also the adoption of AI
I would love to get your perspective and
then I'll jump in to address that
particular question as well Absolutely So
this was definitely one of my favorite
questions But I think I'll talk about it
in the context of some of the other
questions also that I saw So there are
questions that are coming around skills
atrophy how to be up skilled So I saw all
of that too and um I think the
generational piece is really interesting
because I think whichever generation we
are we are
we are assuming everybody else is like us
everybody else is going through the same
change and everybody else learns the same
way right And so that actually is is a
part of some of the challenges here You
know there is a Live conversation around
you know how do we think about junior
talent and how do we bring them in and how
do we upskill But people who are hiring
managers are of a different generation
They learn differently and they um they
they think differently And so that makes
it a little bit difficult with this new
technology around you know how do you how
do you bring these people in who do you
bring them in And how do you create
opportunities for them so that they would
create value as they are learning the job
as well
It's a fascinating question
Right I share one of my own personal
experiences as well I'm an assistant I'm
an adjunct professor and I teach machine
learning and software engineering at
my university And one of the things that I
kind of noticed is when I give these
particular projects and I have students
who are like You call them Generation
Alpha Millennials right But then you also
have certain experts who have 15 years and
20 years of experience And then when I
give them certain projects around building
an agentic architecture or an agent
platform as part of the actual
implementation you see those sort of
nuances and the variances of how every
team or group kind of approaches it Where
you have the current generation which
which would go in open their Claude code
and start building that particular
application while others on the other
extreme end of like fully thinking through
what that particular architecture needs to
be how do you build that entire software
development lifecycle how would you build
these particular models and think about
all of the foundational pieces that would
be required to build an enterprise grade
software So you see that particular
spectrum and but but I think we are at a
very interesting point where we can learn
from all of these different aspects On one
side to be very agile very quickly
prototype build something but on the on
the other end also learn from the best
practices that have been developed over
the past three decades and four decades as
to why those are critical or fundamental
to building enterprise grade Applications
that are scalable so it's it's a fantastic
question and yes it's great to see radical
evolution
and adoption across the generations that
are there
That's amazing I want to take another
question I see like you know multiple
questions coming in with the same line but
the gist of the question is already over
indexing on AI capabilities right As we
are rethinking job redesign
And I think like you know as an industry I
mean right And I think I actually think
that we are a little bit I think you know
too much we are thinking about what is it
that AI can do and therefore what is the
leftover that humans can do And I think
the danger with that way of thinking is
that you know we don't know what the next
eighteen months or three years are going
to look like That end state is truly
unknowable and in a lot of ways on many
different levels And so if you remember
that onion slide that Soya was sharing one
way of thinking about it is You know let's
chase the jobs of tomorrow and skills of
tomorrow and like let's make sure that we
have them But then guess what In eighteen
months we have to reinvent the workforce
again right Another way of thinking about
it is what are the core human foundation
skills that we need to have You know our
ability to problem solve creativity
innovation empathy with users And and what
are the core technical skills that we need
to have so that we can stay resilient You
know that SOC analyst could become the DNA
compliance champion
right Like you know by looking at that
middle layer And if you focus on the
skills and competencies that do not change
that remain relevant I feel like you build
a lot of optionality in the workforce You
bring a lot of flexibility and resilience
both personally and also for the workforce
So yes I do think there is a little bit
of a elimination
substitution You know I guess maybe over
indexing in this story But I think AI has
the ability to substitute humans but it
can also make us super humans
And so it is a little bit up to us
for how we want to think about it and what
side of that story we want our
organizations to be
Kabeh
not to put you on the spot in the last
final two minutes but if I may dare to
it's a question that comes up
significantly on what does that particular
future role of junior talent in an AI
augmented development environment look
like
I know it is something that every
organization is dealing with and it's
something I think we as an industry are
exploring as well
We are we are definitely exploring I can
tell you that there is definitely one
final answer here I think it's one of
those places where we are seeing multiple
models emerge and we are looking at them
and then you know doing iron analysis on
top of it But one of my favorite models
has been um You know similar to legal
industry right Like you know you hire an
associate so that you know for their
ability to learn And you know you don't
know what the legal cases the next three
years might look like but you hire an
associate that you know has the potential
to get there no matter what that future
looks like I think for junior talent it's
going to be like that I think it's going
to be a lot of hiring for the ability to
learn and on learn and the ability to
reinvent yourself and of course like some
core technical capabilities But not as
much double click on the specific
technical capabilities because there is a
very good chance that all of those
technical skills are going to be somewhat
outdated you know by by some future I
would say my advice to anyone who's a
junior person today is that they like
learn something new and keep that muscle
going I think it's very easy to give it up
to AI and like you know stop asking
questions or stop the curiosity Stay
curious even if AI makes it easy not to be
Um and and that's the way that you can you
know keep you know being flexible and
reinvent yourself
I mean the key thing over there is like
what you're suggesting is the entry level
roles don't go away but the ramp may be a
little bit steeper when it comes to the
value
and that's where you need stronger
intentional coaching to be able to
you know nurture that New talent coming
into the workforce
Thank you I think we are at time Want to
pass it on back to Sneha Thank you so much
for all your questions And you're on
standby to help address So please don't
hesitate to reach out to your Gardner reps
And we will be more than happy to share
further analysis
So much Kabeh Vaziri Soyeb for sharing
your insights Before you go just a quick
reminder you can access these additional
resources at the bottom of the page The
insights shared today are just a glimpse
of the objective indispensable guidance
Gartner provides to help CIOs accelerate
decisionmaking drive digital
transformation while partnering
effectively across the organization to
deliver business value from their digital
investments Gartner's solution for CIOs
combines forwardthinking insights
interactive tools expert interactions user
experiences and executivelevel guidance
from seasoned thought partners enabling
CIOs to lead the charge in advancing their
organization's digital strategy and
driving innovation You'll also gain access
to rolespecific benchmarks best practices
and contextualized insights tailored to
your unique challenges Plus ask Gartner
our AIpowered tool for instance access to
trusted Gartner expertise To learn more
simply follow the link on this slide and
connect with your Gartner representative
today Let's explore how we can help you
and your team accelerate impact
You can always also join us at the Gartner
IT Symposium Expo to join thoughtprovoking
sessions led by industry visionaries Meet
oneonone with a Gartner analyst to refine
your strategy network with fellow leaders
and explore the latest innovation from top
solution providers
Please follow us on social media and sign
up to our biweekly newsletter to receive
the latest Gartner IT insights and updates
across research conferences and more It's
all curated specifically for IT leaders
and decision makers
You can access all of these resources from
the bottom of the page Thus you can get
Mugartner insights access additional
resources and see upcoming and ondemand
webinars at Mugartnercomwebinars
And lastly please don't forget to rate
this session and share your feedback on
the insights provided To submit your
rating click the rate session link below
the player A box will open for you to
select one to five hearts with five hearts
being the top rating We also welcome your
feedback on the insights provided in the
leave for the feedback box All right With
that I'd like to again thank our presenter
and of course Whether you're new to
Gartner or an existing client thank you
for joining us today Goodbye