Lucas
Kobat Gartner enterprise architecture EA
AI transformation value orchestrator
The
Hello and welcome to this Gartner webinar
Leading Enterprise Architecture in twenty
twenty six a guide for AI enabled
transformation
Your task is driving stronger performance
on your organization's mission critical
priorities To do that you need trusted
guidance that provides clarity not just
information
At Gartner we deliver that clarity by
combining forwardlooking insights from
twentyfive hundred experts with rigorous
proprietary research methodologies
Our perspective is uniquely informed by
our handson work with five hundred
thousand client interactions across every
major function geography industry and
sector
We don't just provide the business and
technology insights We work with you to
apply them equipping your team with
practical tools and expert guidance to
achieve your goals
So whether you're a new to Gartner or one
of our existing clients today you'll get
actionable objective insights rooted in
human intelligence to help you move
forward with confidence
I'm Robert the operator for this session
Before we get started I have a few tips to
enhance your webinar experience
Here are our rules of engagement for
watching this session We'll pause a moment
to give you time to review them
Around the video player you find a variety
of ways to interact with the session We
encourage you to participate by clicking
the Ask a Speaker box to submit your
questions and thoughts about this program
You can submit a question honestly or if
you choose your name title and company can
be visible along with your question
Navigate to the bottom of the page
download additional resources
Throughout the program you can rate the
session and share feedback Submit your
rating Locate the rate session link below
the player A box will open up for you to
select one to five hearts Please note that
five hearts is the top rating
Share your feedback on the insights
provided and leave for the feedback box
and then click send
Webinar is being recorded Watch this
presentation again and find more great
insights on the minute at
gartnercomwebinars
And now I'd like to welcome Gartner's
director analyst and chief of research
Lucas Kobat Lucas thanks for joining us
And now
thanks Robert and thanks everyone for
joining today Really excited to be here
with you Um like Robert said my name is
Lucas Kobat I'm the chief of research for
enterprise architecture here at Gartner
and it's my honor to facilitate this
session today with you all
So Robert went over some of our legal and
compliance rules that we always have to
share with you Really there's there's one
real ground rule for today and that is to
please ask questions We have a very large
audience but we want to make this as
interactive as we possibly can And the way
that you can do that is you can use the
ask the speaker box to enter questions
throughout our session So without further
ado and in the famous words of Peter Pan
Come on everybody because here we go
All right Our agenda for today is pretty
straightforward We're going to look at
three key issues The first is we're going
to look at the state of enterprise
architecture in two thousand twentysix
The second is we're going to look at how
you can lead enterprise architecture
success in twenty twenty six and beyond
and then finally we're going to wrap up
with some pragmatic steps that you can
take When we end our session here today so
that you can get started
toward achieving your goals and success in
the enterprise architecture function that
you call home
All right let's get started
This slide should really not come as a
surprise to anyone who's been in the
practice of enterprise architecture for
any given period of time
What we know is that
enterprise architects serve a wide ranging
group of stakeholders from delivery teams
to business leaders to even executive
teams However each one of these
stakeholder groups has long had challenges
with the way that heads of enterprise
architecture and their teams deliver
decision guidance and support Uh when uh
we look at delivery teams right Often we
hear that EA just slows down delivery
We're a roadblock we're a governance
inhibitor right For business leaders they
just want their shiny new tool now right
They they oftentimes are trying to figure
out how they can get around architecture
governance
And then finally on the righthand side
there with executive leaders oftentimes
our guidance and support
is
Is too technical and
ITcentric for their needs
What this leads to is you can see across
the bottom row there is that delivery
teams and the rest of IT start to ask Well
can we just replace EA with AI
capabilities
or for business leaders they ask You know
why do we even have this EA team What is
their purpose And then for our executive
partners you know they they look in the
work that we provide and they say What
value is here What value is being provided
And like I said this comes as no surprise
to anyone who's been in EA for any given
period of time and it's backed up by the
data that we most recently got from our
2026 Heads of Enterprise Architecture
signature survey You can see some of those
data points on the right hand side of the
slide there What we know is that Heads of
VA are least confident in securing EA
resources or additional budget or staff
Being able to help organizations determine
and navigate the impacts of our volatile
world and also scaling artificial
intelligence both within their own EA
teams and across the enterprise
And
just compounding on top of that we know
that thirtyfour percent of heads of AI
cite the inability to effectively
demonstrate value and return on investment
in an EA capability And what that ends up
with right is just a simple extension of
today's EA function not being enough not
being not being sufficient to really
thrive in this next AI era that we find
ourselves in We really do need a complete
reimagination of enterprise architecture
within our organizations
And one reason for that right This
is again not a surprise is that AI sprawl
is creating technology risk You see you
know AI capabilities are hitting today's
organizations
like a tidal wave You see lots of
different AI capabilities with high rates
of adoption already in 2026 and it's
really only been two to three years that
organizations have been on this journey
There's lots of initiatives going on to
enable AIready data or to push AI to the
edge or to provide every employee with
generative capabilities or even you know
starting really just this last year and
into this year incorporating AI agents
into workflows and leveraging composite AI
to get even more finetuned capabilities by
pairing machine learning with generative
tools Um and you see at the top of the
title wave there are agentic systems
really being the next great leap As we
found in our CEO survey that a majority of
CEOs are planning to adopt autonomous
systems or autonomous operations
operations or systems operating primarily
without human involvement really in just
the next three years
But that creates a lot of risk right And
we see some of those risk examples on the
right hand side data privacy exposures
cybersecurity and operational risks
regulatory challenges increased AI and
associated cloud costs All of these things
are things that each one of those
stakeholder groups from the last
slidedelivery teams business partners and
executive groups All of these stakeholder
groups are looking to somebody in the
organization to help and enterprise
architecture is well positioned to do so
But we have to be able to do it
effectively
But what does that mean right What does
that mean in terms of how we can provide
effective guidance and support Well one of
the ways is within the IT portfolio
However we also face a big challenge here
There's a lot of influencing factors on
the fact that most easy cost reduction
options have already been exhausted Cost
optimization has been a top priority for
organizations for the past several years
given growth ambitions and technology
investment advancements in AI
Organizations are seeking to trim costs in
other places to accelerate their AI
programs Geopolitical tensions I mean this
is in the news every single day at the top
of the headlines in many different regions
of the world creating supply chain issues
creating issues in markets and in sourcing
raw materials and also climate events
Right And all of these factors contribute
to the need for cost optimization But
organizations have already been through
the process of
cutting what they can in the short term
And honestly cutting too much in the short
termthose immediate cost reductionsthey
usually don't go far enough And if we go
too far we actually risk jeopardizing
those growth ambitions that our
organizations have in the first place
Whereas you know long term with
looking towards the future those cuts are
usually harder to do and they may not get
done in time to make a difference So
really where organizations are stuck at is
this balancing act of how can we free up
the resources necessary to fuel the growth
that we see and that we need while also
balancing the short term risks and costs
that we face today
And all of this sort of compiles on top of
each other And what we see is that you
know with global forces driving continued
turmoil the mission for organizations is
pretty clear If you play along with me
with the recent success of the Artemis II
Mission We need to launch a proverbial
orbital exit that cuts through the noise
and above the fray right As enterprise
architects and heads of enterprise
architecture teams what we really need to
do in twenty twenty six and beyond is help
the organization leverage the benefits of
AI and its relentless advance and maturity
while mitigating those risks Help the
organization to navigate economic and
geopolitical volatility
and to really step up to the plate and
help propel our organization's growth
ambitions
and
close the gap in terms of our IT
organization's ability to deliver
So this like I said all wraps up to just
one simple fact the EA discipline faces an
identity crisis Multiple stakeholder
groups that we've served for many many
years are all facing challenges They all
have needs that are really not being met
by EA today and so an iterative approach
to improving your EA function is not
likely to succeed So instead what are the
things that we can do to ensure success in
2026 and beyond for EA
And that's what we're going to focus on
right We're going to focus on that in our
second key issue I see some good questions
already coming into the chat here Things
like what are the most common AI use cases
for the EA function
what are the most common EA activities
that no longer scale There's a lot of good
questions here We are going to get to some
of these in our session here today If not
always feel free to schedule an
interaction with one of our experts on our
enterprise architecture team to be happy
to go into more detail with you
Let's get into this next session because I
think we're going to address some of these
questions that are coming up in here in
the chat These are great questions So how
can we lead an EA success in 2026 and
beyond Well the process is pretty simple
right We make EA mission critical We have
to establish our function as a mission
critical change agent that helps our
organization adapt to global volatility
high growth and pervasive AI How do we do
that Well there's five imperatives There's
five things that we need to do One is we
need to step into the AI leadership vacuum
The second is that we need to untangle the
AI rollout The third is that we need to
begin building dynamic architectures The
fourth is that we need to guide technology
investments And the fifth is that we need
to reimagine EA with AI So these five
things are what we're going to talk about
today These five imperatives are what we
need to start to act on to deliver success
from EA in 2026 and into the future
All right let's get started with the first
imperative
This has to do with stepping into the AI
leadership vacuum And what do we mean by
that Well Gartner's belief is that we need
heads of VA should seize the opportunity
and step into any AI leadership vacuum to
own and drive AI direction and value Why
do we believe this Because currently AI is
the technology that CEOs believe is going
to fundamentally disrupt their business in
the next three years That's not a surprise
What we do know is a challenge though is
that many organizations do not have a
dedicated AI leader and what this leads to
is decentralized experimentation
Redundancy duplication of effortall of the
things that we try to
mitigate from an enterprise architecture
perspectiveand so what we can do and on
the next slide we'll get into thisis we
can you know know that if we step into an
AI leadership vacuum we're going to be
able to help the organization navigate
this big uncertainty And we're already
starting to see this happen right This is
from our signature survey for heads of
enterprise architecture Sixtysix percent
of EA leaders report that they are
personally invested in becoming an AI
expert by the end of 2026
This partners with a lot of other data
points that we see with heads of EA
already stepping into this AI leadership
role And what that means is there's a
couple steps that we have to take to
really fully realize that role and be able
to guide our organization
Organizations forward and the first is we
have to make the case for AI leadership
Right In some organizations heads of EA
are being asked to take this In some
organizations we're not right Maybe AI
leadership is distributed across a CIO a
CTO a head of data analytics Maybe it sits
in other areas like the business or other
functions like with a chief operating
officer But what we know is that heads of
enterprise architecture have a unique
perspective between both where our
business is trying to go and what our IT
organization can enable And what is
realistic in terms of our AI ambitions and
the roadmap that it's actually going to
take to get there so we need to make the
case to our leadership teams That EA is
the best home for a coordinated enterprise
AI effort that's really going to deliver
on the ambitions that the organization has
The second thing that we need to do
Is that we need to monitor emerging AI
capabilities and evaluate their value and
risk This is one of the biggest challenges
with AI today Is that vendors Are one
continuing to mature their capabilities at
record pace and two a lot of what they are
promising is simply just marketing hype
And so the combination of those two things
makes it very foggy in terms of what's
realistic what's feasible and what can we
actually get value from across all of the
potential AI technologies capabilities and
vendors that are out there As a head of EA
and as the enterprise architecture team we
need to be the source of truth and the
objective voice in the room about what's
possible and really what's not and quite
simply what needs AI and what simply does
not in today's organization
The third step here is that we need to
orchestrate stakeholder alignment and
influence investment decisions This goes
back to that portfolio balancing act that
we were talking about a couple minutes ago
There's a lot of competing demands Every
single business unit in your organization
is going to think they need something
different when it comes to AI Every
delivery team is going to think that they
have their favorite model or workflow or
what have you What we need to do is bring
everybody together and get everybody
moving in the same direction And what that
what that's going to come down to is some
tough decisions around where we invest in
a specific AI technologies and where we
don't But if we don't create that
orchestrated and coordinated approach
again what we're going to see is that AI
sprawl that tidal wave that hits our
organization creates undue complexity and
a lot of technical debt along the way
Next step that we have to take in order to
step into this AI leadership vacuum is
that we need to establish adaptive
governance across business and IT This is
a concept that we've been talking about at
Gartner for some time Is this concept of
adaptive governance Really there's four
flavors or four styles of an adaptive
governance framework They range all the
way from control style governance which is
done through rules and compliance To
outcome style governance where we
prioritize and triage based on value To
agile style governance where
we are able to continuously reprioritize
and continuously reassess initiatives all
the way to autonomous styles of governance
And what this really means is introducing
new and kind capabilities that our
organization might not have had before to
automate governance processes and even
create workflows that are conducive to
agentic ways of working Um even bringing
in things like Guardian Agent To
help to mitigate the AI sprawl that's
already happening and also create an
environment where AI capabilities can
successfully bring value but within
guardrails
And then finally what we need to do to
fully realize this AI leadership role that
sits out there for most of us with in our
grasp is to establish an AI watchtower to
measure success And so this what we're
what we're talking about across these
steps is really the concept of sort of an
elevator architect right We need to be
able to get into the weeds to help
delivery teams move as fast as they
possibly can with these AI initiatives We
need to step up a level and help our
portfolio teams our business partners
build a roadmap of initiatives That's
going to drive toward success and then
finally we need to again sort of move out
of the orbital chaos and get above that
fray and into a tower where we can see
what's working and what's not working and
then quickly kill off the things that are
not working prune that portfolio to
something that's really going to drive
success for our organization
Um before we move on to the next
imperative let me just check the chat Um
Oh there's a good question here What's the
relevance of TOGAF framework in the world
of AI It's a great question from Vicron's
here So Gartner's position on EA
frameworks has been clear for a long time
right We do not advocate for any specific
EA framework We don't say that one is
better than the other The purpose of an EA
framework is simply for inspiration Right
what is out there What is possible What
does our organization actually need An EA
framework should never serve as aspiration
Right we should never be seeking to
execute an EA framework down to the letter
of the law on every single bullet point
Because what we're then doing is we're
doing EA for the sake of doing EA rather
than using the EA discipline and EA
concepts to push our organization forward
and realize some of the ambitions that our
organization has like what we're talking
about here with AI So it's a great
question Great question Um let's see Uh
one more question before we move on here
David's got a question here How does EA
handle AI teams saying they are the ones
to drive the architecture and EA is just a
technology architecture David you're
hitting on something that I was mentioning
just briefly before which is in some
organizations the head of EA is being told
by the CIO or even the CEO Hey you need
to be our AI leader You need to bring the
organization forward and figure out what's
the path for us when it comes to AI In
some other organizations right that that
request has been made to other groups That
really is the third step in sort of this
staircase diagram that we're looking at
here on the page Even
different places of the organization that
have been given this responsibility of hey
run forward with AI look at the
capabilities that we need the technologies
that we need tell us what we need so we
can make the right investments A lot of
times if it's given to the data and
analytics group or if it's given to the
COO or if it's given to you know the head
of enterprise applications All of these
individuals are coming at it from their
sort of siloed lens The benefit we have as
enterprise architects is we're able to
look across all these groups and say What
does the organization really need So I
would you know say we don't want to be
combative right That's not going to help
anybody But what we can do is we can be
collaborative right with those groups who
have been given those responsibilities and
say hey look I know you've been asked to
do this These other three groups in our
organization have also been asked to move
forward really fast with AI Let's you know
come together and see who's working on
what Make sure that we're not you know
putting forth any sort of redundant effort
that we're not investing in duplicative
capabilities And that we're really putting
our organization on the best path forward
That's a critical role that a head of
enterprise architecture can play that
really very few others in an organization
can So great question David
Let's let's keep moving We're going to
move to our second imperative for our
session today of the five imperatives that
we need to act on now to realize EA
success in twenty twenty six and beyond
The second again no surprise has to deal
with AI
This actually moves beyond just taking
that leadership role but it gets into a
little more the nitty gritty on what we
need to do to realize AI success So
Gartner's position Gartner's belief here
is that to scale enterprise AI value we as
heads of VA need to sort of abandon our
old ways of working those designfirst
habits and instead pursue what we call an
enable deploy and adapt approach So let's
get into what that means just a little bit
because I know we'll all have questions on
that
So when it comes to untangling the rollout
of AI across the enterprise what we know
from again our signature survey that we
just ran for heads of enterprise
architecture is that about only forty
percent of EA leaders believe that current
AI investments Will have a materially
positive impact on their organization's
financial performance Again this comes
from just sort of the pessimism that we're
probably seeing as enterprise architects
We see all these different parts of the
organization running in different
directions The decentralized
experimentation when it comes to AI and so
how do we actually solve for that Right
How do we get different stakeholder groups
within our organization to start picking
the right AI investments To start making
the right bets and to stop sort of running
over each other in the process so that we
can actually get to that enterprise AI
scale that's going to push our
organization forward into the future
So how do we do that Right How do we
execute How do we actually untangle the
rollout of AI across the enterprise Well
the first thing that we need to do is we
need to enable rapid and safe AI
experimentation
What
What does that mean right Well what it
means is we need to again using that sort
of elevator architect analogy We need to
get down into the weeds with our delivery
teams We need to see what they're actually
working on what they're considering when
it comes to AI investment and it really
comes from what their business partners
are asking them to do So this comes into
the conversation of a lot of AI use case
conversation Right and there was actually
a question in the chat just a couple
minutes ago about what AI use cases are
most prominent or most relevant for an EA
team We can absolutely talk about that and
we're going to talk about that towards the
end of our session today One of the things
that we also need to talk about is what
are the AI use cases that are most
relevant to your organization and how do
we quickly start to execute on those Right
so that's step one in terms of how we
untangle the rollout Right and we mark out
some bullet points on what that means here
provide lightweight clear and practical
guardrails encourage action over
documentation Let's not become roadblocks
to AI success by saying we need a
seventyfive page solution architecture
document before anybody does anything
That's not going to put us in the best
position to succeed The second step that
we need to act on here is we need to
deploy evolving best practices and
patterns So as we're working alongside
these delivery teams we're going to see
what's working and what's not and what the
benefit we have as enterprise architects
and heads of enterprise architecture Is we
can then take those learnings and we can
promote them across the organization using
all of the available channels that we
already have We can work with our
executive partners We can work with our
business leaders We can work with our
delivery teams and communities Many of you
probably have centers of excellence or
communities of practice that you can plug
into and promote these ways of working
that will help delivery teams only move
faster and in a safer way when it comes to
AI experimentation
And finally we have the third step here
right Adapt So we need to adapt
architecture to scale AI success and that
really comes down into the conversation of
what are we going to scale what are we
going to kill and we have to be very clear
and very objective about what we do Here
and again this is less about the science
of architecture and as I like to call it
sort of the art of architecture Because
what we're doing is oftentimes we're
playing the role of even a therapist for a
lot of these business leaders They are you
know very invested in their shiny new
object They want their project to succeed
but oftentimes what's best for the
organization is for that project to be
shut down Those resources To be freed up
and for them to be reinvested elsewhere
And as a head of enterprise architecture
what we have to do is we have to be
able to bring that individual to the table
bring them into the fold and help them
understand the benefits of what they're
going to gain from letting go Right And
and so that comes down to managing that
portfolio
playing that balancing act and and again
like I said sometimes even playing the
role of therapist to get people to to come
along and orchestrate all the stakeholders
that we need
All right Imperative three is about
building dynamic and adaptive
architectures This is a new concept that
we've been sort of outlining here at
Gartner and I'm excited to share it with
you Before we move forward just want to
see some of these questions that are
coming through in the chat
Ian asks a question
Our organization has a central AI center
of excellence separate from the main
architecture team How common is this and
is this best practice Yeah so Ian again
this is the point I was trying to make
about stepping into that AI leadership
vacuum There really is no common practice
There's really no
even sort of best practice that's already
been established about how you lead AI
within an organization What I have seen
multiple times across multiple teams and
multiple industries Is that the head of EA
is sort of attached initially with how do
we get AI off the ground and then to run
it operationally Sometimes we turn to that
center of excellence and that center of
excellence is basically a cross section of
all of the stakeholders that we would have
to be orchestrating Right So going back to
that third step in that staircase diagram
That's really our job is figuring out who
in the organization needs to be in that
center of excellence and if that center of
excellence is already established it's how
do we get all of those players to work
together in the best possible way that
they can Um so again great question great
question And if everybody if you see a
question that's being asked and you have
the same one just go ahead and give it a
thumbs up I'm looking at the most voted
questions here just so that we can get the
the questions answered that everybody has
the most interest in
Before we move on to the third imperative
just looking at time here we probably have
time for one more James you've got a
question How do you deal with the
development
and
business teams' inability and
unwillingness to adequately assess the
business benefits and actual cost of AI
before building something that might not
make sense The rush to doing POCs and
pilots without any clarity of business
value
Absolutely absolutely
So that's where that conversation about
use cases becomes really critical Um and
James what I would recommend is as heads
of enterprise architecture we have to if
we haven't already started we have to
start doing our homework on the top use
cases for our organization That means
staying on top of industry press that
means having real conversations with our
business partners today that means looking
at what's actually feasible from AI
vendors and their marketplaces of
capabilities Um and then you know from a
Gartner perspective we absolutely can help
with that If you haven't seen it what we
have is we actually have an entire AI use
case dashboard that is broken down by
industry that's broken down by functional
area of the organization whether it be
marketing whether it be supply chain HR IT
you name it And we're we're starting to
see all of these use cases that actually
have promise We're figuring out which
organizations have done it successfully
We're providing them as case studies and
we're actually giving you a ranking of AI
use cases In terms of business benefit and
then feasibility right So and and risks
included in that feasibility metric as
well So you can start to if you haven't
already go into that dashboard start
seeing what's relevant for your
organization and bring that into the
conversations you are having Excuse me
with your with your teams right Because
That's the only way we're going to get
people to consider what's going to work
and what is not going to work is if we
have some sort of way to to think about
this simply right business value versus
feasibility and then start plotting our
prioritized use cases against it And that
doesn't mean that we you slow people down
on the move to POCs What it means is that
we at least just ask the right questions
before we get there
All right just looking at time here Let's
jump into this third imperative about
building dynamic and adaptive
architectures
So again Gartner's position is that head
to VA must build dynamic architectures
that adapt to shifts in enterprise
conditions
So there's a really interesting data point
that I wanted to bring to people's
attention
We asked about this actually just in our
last agenda poll that we got back just a
couple weeks ago and what we saw is that
only 25 of HEDSVA are very confident in
their ability to adapt architectures to
rapid business changes And why does this
matter Well when we were going over sort
of the macro challenges that organizations
face today we were looking at Things like
geopolitical instability right And one
risk that's really risen to the top of a
lot of organizations' profiles today is
sovereignty right Cloud sovereignty AI
sovereignty you know business sovereignty
Where are we actually going to be allowed
to operate and where can we source
capabilities and which partners can we
work with based on where they're at in the
world That has a immediate impact on our
architectures because a lot of them break
if you know two regions of the world
suddenly cannot trade with each other or
you know the level of
fiscal policy that's being implemented in
a certain area just becomes too much of a
burden and we then you know cannot operate
feasibly in that area or source from that
area And so the the thing that we need
actually is a whole new way about thinking
about the the enterprise architecture for
the organization
And so what we're starting to call this is
we're starting to call this a dynamic
state architecture But before I get to
that concept let's just play out
traditionally what happens Right So as as
heads of enterprise architecture as people
that lead EA teams or as enterprise
architects ourselves what we always do is
we say Well
Where does the organization want to go
right So what does our future state
architecture look like And we look at lots
of different things within that future
state architecture We'll look at our
business and technical capabilities We'll
look at our delivery model We'll look at
our current technology investments We'll
look at the governance model that we have
in place The outcomes that the
organization is trying to achieve and say
all right well how does everything need to
fit together What does everything need to
look like in that future state And then
we'll we'll say all right Well if that's
where we want to go what do we currently
have And we'll look at that current state
architecture Right same same building
blocks but just from the lens of what we
already have The challenge is is that our
organization moves faster than we realize
those future states right And so what we
have is this future state this beautiful
piece of you know architecture diagram
work that we've done on the right hand
side of the page
But our organization's current state is
already maybe five or six iterations past
what we started with By the time we even
get close to realizing that feature state
architecture And that is because of a lot
of the different risks that we've just
been talking about geopolitical
instability
cost optimization sovereignty as a risk
Right And so what we need to do is instead
of planning for a fixed longterm vision we
need to monitor in real time how our
current state is changing and then
reconfigure dynamically
And what that requires is it requires us
to look at each one of those building
blocks whether it be business and
technical capabilities whether it be our
delivery model or the way that we do
technology investment Or how we govern the
IT portfolio We need to look at all of
those different things and we need to say
how can we even shift those things to be
more autonomous those things to be more
automated or for them to at least be able
to reconfigure dynamically and more
modularly than they have been before And
so there's a lot that we can get into here
We're not going to have time Cover it all
today If you have further questions on
this this would be a great one to follow
up with one of the analysts on our team
because they can unpack each one of these
building blocks and help your organization
figure out Well how do we move from sort
of those static stagnant future state
architectures That really never get
realized to actually being able to adapt
and shift with our organization as these
new enterprise conditions are introduced
So again a very fascinating area a very
real thing that we all need to be working
on Let's see are there other questions
here in the chat that we should be
answering
Let's see a lot of AI questions A lot of
great AI questions So
somebody asked What are the key artifacts
that you would expect EA to ask solution
teams working on AI projects to produce
Would you have templates to share
Yeah absolutely So this goes back to sort
of like our abandon old design first
habits
Sometimes we're not going to have the time
to put together a seventyfive page
solution architecture document
If we really want to enable and realize
the value from a particular AI capability
what we should do is we should do sort of
that you know business of value versus
feasibility risk analysis and then we
should have at least considered the
alternative solutions in terms of how
we're going to source this or we're going
to build by blend But then beyond that
right Sometimes we just there's There's
just not the time for those traditional
artifacts and so what I would recommend is
instead of pursuing assurance by document
is pursue assurance by partnership Right
actually get down alongside these delivery
teams and help them move faster See the
risks that they as they come and you're
going to be able to help those delivery
teams navigate a lot of that complexity
that we try to mitigate by packing it all
into a document that can then be
referenced at a later point in time
Um
let's see Another question here Is it
worthwhile to ready EA pattern and
framework guidance as policy in markdown
format for inclusion in a context layer
for agentic solutions to consume
Dave you're getting ahead of me here We're
absolutely going to talk about this when
we wrap up with reimagining EA with AI Um
But I will just say a piece of that
actually is is very important to what
we're looking at here on the page
about building dynamic and adaptive
architectures The orchestration layer
within our digital foundations within our
technology stack is going to become more
important than ever Right the ability to
orchestrate and multiagent systems Right
every vendor is pushing that they have a
multiagent system whether it be Salesforce
whether it be SAP whether it be Oracle
whoever it is Right
it's great that they are providing agents
to our organization How do all of those
agents work together to actually
accomplish goals that our organization has
And so that's where that orchestration
layer becomes more critical than ever has
been And we as enterprise architects and
people who lead enterprise architecture
teams we need to be very clear on what
that orchestration layer needs to look
like and we need to start building it But
again we can't build it in a fashion of
here's what it's going to look like three
years from now in a nice pretty picture We
need to realize that the current state of
our organization's orchestration layer
even Is going to change seven times before
we get it right and so we need to be
very in tune with how that is changing and
help design those changes and reconfigure
when things are not working Right So again
that that that ties into what we're
talking about here with dynamic and
adaptive architectures and then how we
build EA guidance in a way that can be
consumed by agents It's a fascinating
question We'll get to it here in just a
couple minutes So so bear with me
All right we've got about twenty minutes
left in our time together today Time is
flying We've got two more imperatives that
I want to talk about and then there's
going to be a poll question We'll wrap up
with some pragmatic steps The fourth
imperative that we're going to look at
here in terms of the five things that we
got to do to drive success in 2026
is that we have to
both act as an investment advisor and a
venture capitalist in terms of helping to
guide our CIO in balancing those immediate
and long term IT investments Again this
goes back to the sort of that macro
challenge about you know those easy cuts
have been exhausted So what do we do now
And you know what we see in terms of the
data that we get back from heads of
enterprise architecture is that seventy
nine percent of EA leaders claim that they
are responsible for the IT cost
optimization strategy and held accountable
for actual cost optimization realized
Right so this is factoring into our annual
goals This is how our performance is being
measured Are we able to successfully
balance those shortterm costcutting
strategies with the longterm cost
optimization approaches that we need to
really drive growth in the future And how
do we balance those two things for our CIO
And so what we are positioning here at
Gartner is that you really need to play
both roles at the same time So we need to
be both the financial advisor and the
venture capitalist And what does that
really mean Well the first is that we need
to as the financial advisor pursue those
IT cost reduction and optimization
initiatives We need to be able to
eliminate waste maximize value and align
IT spend with business strategy And at the
same time and on the other hand we need to
be the CIO's venture capitalist We need to
be on the lookout scanning the horizon for
those technology investment opportunities
We need to be able to identify assess and
enable those investments that are going to
drive innovation and
competitive advantage within our
organization It was funny We were sharing
some of these positions and some of these
findings with with a group of heads of
enterprise architecture a couple weeks ago
and one of them spoke up and they said Hey
you know my CIO came to my office
the other day and they said that yeah your
role as the head of enterprise
architecture is that you are now the
venture capitalist for our organization
And I think this just rings true because
we see that tidal wave of AI capabilities
crashing in on our organization We see
emerging technologies beyond AI whether it
be you know post quantum cryptography or
physical AI You know the the bringing of
AI capabilities into polyfunctional or
humanoid robots These things are not that
far off in terms of their impact or
ability to impact organizations today We
as heads of enterprise architecture need
to be experts in The technology in sort of
that twelve to eighteen month maybe twenty
four month horizon that has that risk or
opportunity for our organization and be
guiding our stakeholder groups on how they
can actually act on and realize value from
those technologies now
Great So that brings us through four of
the things that we need to do today to
realize success for EA in 2026
Just looking at the chat
Ian Ian you've got another great question
here A lot of people also had the same
question Looks like a lot of thumbs up on
this one Are you going to take into
account different levels of maturity In
different organizations yeah So when we
gather survey data we make sure that we
get a cross section of
industry of EA profile right So when you
look at the the findings that we're
sharing with you this is not from the most
mature clients right I would say this is
actually where you know sort of the middle
of the bell curve is in terms Of where
heads of enterprise architecture are at
what they're doing the challenges that
they're considering If you're in you know
more of a leading EA practice versus more
like a mainstream or conservative EA
practice
The way that you apply these findings or
the way that you pursue success might
change a little bit right Your mileage may
vary but these imperatives remain the same
These are all things that we need to be
focusing on as heads of VA and making sure
that we have an answer to when somebody
comes and asks us Hey what are you doing
about this For our organization Now what
we're turning to now with this last
imperative
is we're turning a little bit inward right
And a lot of you have been asking
questions in the chat about this How can
we reimagine EA with AI Well our position
at Gartner is that heads of EA who don't
proactively use AI to optimize EA
activities will become a roadblock to
increasing demand from business and IT
stakeholders and that's the last thing we
want right Going all the way back to the
beginning
We know that our stakeholders see us as a
roadblock more times than they than they
probably should We know that we sort of
face an identity crisis because we have
too many stakeholders to serve with too
many problems So how can we scale our
decision support increase the capacity of
our teams and deliver success A lot of
it's going to come down to our ability to
successfully integrate AI capabilities
into our function
Um and what we know is that this is
already happening You guys are already
doing this This comes from again that
survey I've cited a couple times our
signature survey for heads of enterprise
architecture Um this is the percentage of
AI augmented EA activities by year So last
year you said that 14 of EA work was
augmented by AI This year 23
We asked you all what you thought about
next year and you said thirty
percentalmost a third of EA activities are
going to be augmented by some sort of AI
capability So what does that look like
What does that mean Well at Gartner we've
come up with a path forward to actually
help transform the EA operating model
using AI And I want to share those steps
with you today at a high level If you have
interest in any going deeper on any of
these steps obviously our team would be
happy to Spend some time one on one with
you getting in digging into how we can
enact these steps at your organization But
the first one is that we just simply need
to assess AI's potential for It's a first
step of moving away from sort of that
traditional
EA model and our journey toward an AI
enabled EA operating model And what that
looks like right is we need to think
through what are the use cases Again going
back to the conversation we had about how
EA helps the enterprise This is how we
help ourselves now We look at the use
cases that are being provided by EA
vendors EA tool vendors that other AI
tools are offering You know maybe we have
an enterprise license with a particular
vendor What kind of capabilities that can
they provide that can augment the work
that we're already doing EA that can
offload some of the responsibilities from
our architects who are already
too time constrained and too spread thin
So that's step one Step two is that we
need to organize for an AI augmented EA So
this means how our AI capability is going
to come alongside our architects And what
is the sort of organizational model that
we're going to deploy Right are we going
to have a distributed model where we have
architects spread out across the
organization We're going to have a
centralized model where we have architects
being plugged into the most impactful
projects and then maybe we use AI
capabilities almost as toolmates Sitting
alongside those delivery teams that are
distributed and giving them the guidance
and support that they need What is the
structure going to look like for that
The next step on that journey is to
identify those highvalue EA AI tools Right
So what are the tools out there that can
do what we need to do from an EA
perspective but in a way that makes them
automated or even
autonomous Once we do that right Then we
need to also at the same time audit EA
tools for AI readiness So you know this is
again what I was saying about AI tools
enterprise licenses to AI vendors are
going to get us part of the way
EA tools and EA vendors that are
specifically integrating AI capabilities
for the things that we already do That's
another spot to look for How do we bring
these capabilities into our organization
into our function
After that we need to mitigate AI specific
risks Again these are risks that are
more known than they ever have been before
right So hallucinations poor data quality
What are the specific risks that we're
going to face when we're trying to bring
AI capabilities into our organization
And then prove AI enabled value again Like
anything we do with EA we probably should
not be doing this with a big bang approach
What we should do is we should try certain
use cases within our EA function test that
they are working test them with a small
number of stakeholders and then after
we've proved that those use cases are
showing value Then scale that as a way of
working across the organization Whether it
be roadmap generation whether it be
reference architecture generation whether
it be architecture governance reviews
whether it be whatever AI use cases we're
pursuing from an EA standpoint Make sure
that those things are working and then
scale Um and then lead by example right We
just talked about how as heads of VA we
have a critical role to play in driving
the AI direction of the entire
organization That we sort of need to step
into that leadership vacuum and what
better way to do it than to show that we
can do it within our own area of the world
right That we are really maximizing the
value that we're getting from AI today and
the reason that we're able To do it is
because we followed this path we followed
these steps Because the way that we've
outlined this path you really can apply to
any part of your organization whether
you're working with supply chain or
finance For marketing right All of these
different areas we can help them follow
and take this same journey But if we've
already done it ourselves it's just proof
of concept that we know what we're talking
about and we have the credibility when we
walk into that room
And then finally that leads us to
AIenabled EA Right So then we we've gotten
to a point where we have transformed that
EA operating model We haven't relied just
on our traditional past and we are able to
to drive a path forward
So that
you know that wraps up those those five
imperatives that we need to focus on for
enterprise architecture to drive success
in 2026 I do want to get to our third
key issue here We've got about nine
minutes left Let me just answer some of
the top questions here that haven't been
addressed Rich you're asking can you
please share a definition list of the four
different AI governance models Awesome
yeah yeah So I was talking about adaptive
governance This is not specific to AI but
they were a control outcome based agile
and autonomous For AI today that
autonomous style of governance is becoming
more critical and more necessary than ever
before And if you either you ask your
account rep from Gartner about that
adaptive governance model they can provide
you all the material you need Or if you
schedule an inquiry or a consultation with
somebody from our team we can deep dive on
that with you a little bit more
All right let's go to the pragmatic steps
And for this I really want to hear from
you because I think we can all learn from
each other here just in terms of what
we're going to do going forward Right
Because change is hard the status quo is
hard We really need to Just at the end of
the day choose our heart and figure out
what it's going to take to be successful
across the rest of 2026 and beyond So
Robert's going to help us out here but
we're going to put up a poll question and
it's going to ask you you know which
imperative is your top focus for the rest
of 2026
Of the five that we talked about today so
stepping into the AI leadership vacuum
untangling the rollout of AI building
dynamic and adaptive architectures
adopting financial advisor and VC hats or
reimagining EA with AI capabilities Um and
after you've answered that answered that
if you could just do us one more favor
because I think everybody's going to get
value from this If you just put in the ask
the speaker chat tell us what the biggest
challenge is to realizing that EA success
Right What are the top things that you're
facing today that are really getting in
the way of you doing any of these things
successfully
Because ultimately you know you all will
have the opportunity to learn from each
other It also helps us at Gartner provide
you the best kind of insights that you're
looking for
Excellent Thank you so much Lucas Yes our
poll is not open We'd like to know what
you are thinking You can see the poll pop
up now on the right right over the slides
In case you can't see the poll on your
screens please refresh your browser window
Once the poll is visible simply select the
answer of your choice and click submit
Once you close the poll we'll display the
final results for everyone to see in the
video player And please continue to enter
your questions for Lucas in the bigger box
I'll also since we're going to have a lot
of people on the Call I may just um sort
of come back in and say Here's what the
most common answers are that we're seeing
in that response part in the ask speaker
chat just so I don't flood the chat with
everyone's responses
Awesome thanks Robert Thanks Robert I know
we've got about five minutes left in our
time together today I want to get as many
of your questions answered as we possibly
can So
here's a question a good question from
Sean It piggybacks off of what we were
just talking about What organizations
consistently get wrong when modernizing EA
for AI Um and Sean this is a great
question Um I actually just published a
research note You can find it on the
Gartner portal Talks about how you
redesign the enterprise architecture role
for the AI era and one of the things that
we see is that we we Unfortunately still
view AI as a silver bullet right And it's
simply not What you can never take away
from the enterprise architecture role is
the human judgment and capacity for
empathy that will never be able to be
coded into any sort of AI capability And
so when it comes to the strategic nature
of the architecture job where we are
designing where we are red mapping where
we are sort of playing that therapist role
between stakeholders All of that actually
just becomes even more critical in an AI
world where AI actually helps is it helps
in sort of mitigating the redundancy of an
enterprise architect's day Right How many
times are we asked by a solution delivery
team What
is the pattern for this technology Again
do we have this application with them Our
portfolio Do we have something that meets
these business requirements that my
partner is asking me for Right all of
those redundant conversations Even simply
putting something like an AI assistant
that is on top of your EA repository that
in and of itself saves you so much time
and saves your architect so much time from
answering those same kind of questions
over and over and over again So AI helps
scale the decision support that we're able
to provide It certainly doesn't replace
the value that an enterprise architect
brings by any means
And Robert looks like we are getting these
poll results back Looks like building
dynamic and adaptive architectures is just
being out Reimagine EA with AI for the
imperative that's going to be our top
focus for the rest of 2026 This is
fascinating and and it really just goes
back to what I was saying before You know
you read the news today it's every single
headline especially just in the past week
Things happening in the Middle East things
happening in Europe things happening in
the US And how all of these different
regions of the world are interacting with
each other This sovereignty risk is really
rising to the top and sort of changing how
organizations think in terms of Where are
our technology vendors located
geographically What sort of resilience
measures are we putting in place for how
our organization how our architectures
change if you know certain decisions are
made Doing that scenario modeling
So absolutely this is definitely a
priority area for Gartner And if you have
questions in this area please feel to
reach out We have teams of analysts who
are working on how we how we change our
architectures to be more dynamic and
adaptive
Excellent Yes and the answers in regards
to that second part we're seeing it kind
of vary all over the place But a lot of
it is whether it's about governments or
having not having a clear leader for those
initiatives in EA of deciding who's really
there kind of
Um
muddies the waters there Um not a strong
backing for EA function within the company
et cetera So really kind of
there's not one common theme or sort of
thing that all they're sort of multiple
and varied
From that from that aspect Lucas But I can
throw it back to you for um question
Yeah thanks Robert Thanks Well we've got
about two and a half minutes left I see
that some folks are having to drop off
Totally understand We all have busy
schedules and busy lives that we're
leading these days
Just in the last minute here Ken asks a
really great question Are there any
specific tools you would recommend to help
enable EA with AI Since this was the
second top focus area for us for the rest
of the year what I would say is yes
absolutely The EA vendor market obviously
they all are working on bringing AI
capabilities into their tool sets Um our
analyst on our team Austin Steinmetz he's
leading the Magic Quadrant for enterprise
architecture tools this year He would be
Great person to have a conversation with
about if you're already using an EA tool
which
capabilities can you bring in to enable
that that AI success with EA or if you're
not using an EA tool
Who might you look at or what other tools
exist out of that outside that EA vendor
market that can satisfy your needs We can
absolutely have that conversation with you
and you sort of tailor it to your specific
situation But great question I know a lot
of people are thinking through that today
All right Well I think that's all the time
we're going to have for questions I see
some more folks are dropping off Thank you
all so much for your time today for
plugging in and digging in with me asking
a lot of great questions I know we covered
a ton of material If you have specific
questions or if you want to think through
with a Gartner expert How you apply these
imperatives or these strategies within
your team within your enterprise Feel free
to give us a call We are always here to
help We just got to know how we can best
do that for you With that I'll sign off
for today and hope to talk to you all and
see you all again real soon Thanks a lot
Yes thank you so much to Lucas To our
audience before you go we've included some
additional resources at the bottom of the
page Quick reminder this webinar is being
recorded You can watch this presentation
again and get more great insights on
demand at garnercomwebinars
Lastly
we do ask you please rate this session And
um to do so a box will um sorry submit
your rating Click rate session below the
player A box open up where you select one
to five hearts Please note that five
hearts is the top rating You share your
feedback on the insights provided in leave
for the feedback box and then click send
That again like to thank our presenter and
of course thank you the audience for
listening Have a great day Goodbye