Ryan Polk Gartner procurement CPO agentic
AI supplier multitier
AI supplier
multitier
Ryan Polk Gartner procurement CPO agentic
AI supplier multitier
Hello and welcome to this Gartner webinar
Steps for procurement to become AIfirst
You have tasked with driving stronger
performance on your organization's
missioncritical priorities To do that you
need
trusted guidance that provides clarity not
just information At Gartner we deliver
that clarity by combining forwardlooking
insights from our 2500 experts with
rigorous proprietary research
methodologies Our perspective is uniquely
informed by our handson work with 500000
client interaction across every major
function geography industry and sector We
don't just provide the business and
technology insights we work with you to
apply them equipping your team with
practical tools and expert guidance to
achieve your goals So whether you're new
to Gartner or one of our existing clients
today you'll get actionable objective
insights rooted in human intelligence to
help you move forward with confidence I'm
Tanya your operator for the session and
before we get started I have a few tips to
enhance your webinar experience
So we have provided our rules of
engagement for watching this session
Please take a moment to familiarize
yourself I'm going to stop on this slide
for a few seconds for all of you to have
a look
All right
So around the video player you will find a
variety of ways to interact with the
session We encourage you to participate by
clicking the As a Speaker box to submit
your questions and thoughts throughout
this program You can either submit a
question anonymously or if you choose your
name title and company can be visible
along with the question Navigate to the
bottom of the page to download additional
resources and throughout the program you
can read the session and share feedback So
to submit your rating locate the rate
session link below the player A box will
open for you to select one to five hearts
Please note that five hearts is a top
rating Share your feedback on the insights
provided in the leave for the feedback box
and click send Also this webinar is being
recorded You can watch this presentation
again and find more great insights on
demand at gartner dot com slash webinars
Now I'd like to welcome Gartner's vice
president analyst Ryan Polk Ryan thank you
so much for joining us and now I'll turn
it over to you
Thank you Tanya and good morning good
afternoon or good evening to everyone
joining today Depending on where you're
where you're at in the world my name is
Ryan Polk and I'll be your your host for
for today's session Today we're we're
going to talk a little bit about AI Right
so a couple months ago we did a session My
colleague Andrew Greenwald did a session
on the future of procurement Where we
touched on some AI related topics and it
was really really well received And as you
can imagine this is an incredibly hot
topic for all of our clientele But really
you can't go a day without hearing hearing
about AI And so we wanted to put on this
webinar to revisit some of those concepts
and really do a bit of a double click on
some of those some of those concepts that
we introduced a couple of months ago
Logistically speaking the way we're going
to handle this webinar is we're going to
look at You know what is impacting
sourcing and procurement from an AI
perspective today Where are we heading How
are we becoming AI first And we're going
to look at that through the lens of a
number of predictions We have several
predictions that I'm going to take you
through Spanning the next three to five
years so we'll take a look at we'll take a
look at those and really take a look at
how do we become AI first because that is
the big question today So we have about
thirty minutes or so of content and then
we are going to open the floor up to Q
and A where I'll be responding to all of
the questions that you have So you'll see
on the right hand side of
The the web browser that you're joining
here today There's going to be a box that
you can submit your questions I would
encourage you to do that and I will filter
through and and go through those questions
towards the end of the session So with all
that said Let me level Let me let me set
the foundation for the conversation today
but just taking a look at some of the
trends that are happening in the AI space
and then we'll kind of get into these
predictions and you know what we believe
needs to happen to actually usher
procurement into the future here So to
begin with I just want to start with you
know a couple a couple or really three
three key or key three trends that are
really happening in the space of AI right
now So on the on the far left hand side
number one From a tech perspective you're
seeing the context windows of AI models
expand quite dramatically in recent years
Now I'm not going to get into you know
precisely what a context window is with
respect to AI but what you need to know is
that it's really the amount of information
That an AI model can take in at any given
point in time while operationalizing an
ask or while responding to a question Now
the reason this matters is because the
more contextual information A model can
ingest if you will while you're
interacting with these models Presumably
the better the more accurate the more
precise that model is going to be Like if
you think about all the information that
we take in as human beings as part of our
daytoday responsibilities as part of our
just interactions throughout life it is a
tremendous amount of data that we're
seeing that we're hearing that we're
feeling All that sensory input allows us
to basically move throughout our lives As
AI context windows expand it makes them
better Right It allows them to take in
more peripheral information to make their
responses more accurate The second kind of
thing that's happening right now and this
has been happening for the last couple of
years is you're seeing models come online
with more and more reasoning abilities
This is kind of like a think before you
speak type functionality If you're using
some of the latest and greatest models
that are out there today you might have
seen this It's called chain of thought
kind of reasoning As you interact with
these models you'll actually see the
models themselves Thinking through their
response before they provide it Again it's
kind of like a think before you speak type
of capability and what this promises is to
reduce the rates of things like
hallucinations and and really just again
allow models to handle more complexity
Right take on activities and respond to
questions that are more complicated in
nature Again kind of ushering these models
up the maturity curve if you will in terms
of what it can actually support And then
on the right hand side You know you're
certainly seeing AI become more and more
multimodal in nature Multimodality here
really is getting at this idea or this
concept that AI can interact with multiple
forms of context and multiple forms of
data So you know if yesterday's models
were largely text in text out
functionality you know today's models and
presumably future models are very much
kind of anything in anything out So think
You know submitting text to a model but
then getting an image out Right We've all
seen that Think about putting an image in
and getting text out or a video in and
getting text out or audio out Right It's
kind of anything in anything out Now
what's interesting About you know the
progress that that that's happening in the
kind of AI technology space is that when
you put some of these trends together when
you when you put some of these progress
lines together what's becoming clear is
that AI is becoming more agentic Right
we've we've heard that word This has been
the buzzword of the last you know twelve
to eighteen months agentic AI And in
procurement and I would argue really the
majority of the business world the way
we're experiencing agentic AI are through
you know AI agents Now from my vantage
point at Gartner there has been a
tremendous amount of quote unquote agent
washing In in the marketplace right You
talk to the vendor community you talk to
various folksthe folks that you know
commentators on on this topic broadly
around AIand everyone's going to have to
claim Everyone's going to claim to have
you know an AI agent for you know
something right It's it's been such a hot
topic Um and I want to just quickly define
how we think about an AI agent So we're
we're kind of on the same page here and
then we'll look at you know how real is
this right Where we actually at So when we
think about an agent an AI agent the way
we kind of conceptualize it is it's it's
an AI model that has the ability
To one perceive an environment and then
two act on that environment independent of
a human prompt and it's that independence
that is a really really big red line in
the sand that we have to pay attention to
To here because we're not talking about a
simple copilot that has the ability to
kind of do really cool things but is
reliant on the human for prompting An AI
agent goes a step further and it allows it
really gives the the model the ability to
action something without that human
intervention Right that's a really big
kind of red line in the sand a you know
delineating line between you know these
copilots that maybe we've been using for
the last couple of years and and what
everyone's kind of talking about And to be
sure we've seen the emergence of You know
some narrowly focused AI agents in
sourcing and procurement There's
negotiations agents that are out there
There's some spend analytics agents that
are out there You know we're beginning to
hear more and more about these
orchestration agents Right That's been
another big hot topic in sourcing and
procurement Um but this is certainly still
very much A futureoriented sort of
conversation We've seen a lot of pilots
but we haven't seen these broadly at scale
quite yet And I want to get into to some
of the reasons maybe why And this is going
to bring me to kind of one of the first
predictions that we have
Around kind of the agentication of of
sourcing and procurement and one of the
things that we believe is that through
twenty twenty seven Only twenty percent of
procurement organizations will have
sufficient data and process maturity to
use multiagent systems But those that do
right so that twenty percent that do are
going to gain real competitive advantage
over those who don't Now I want to break
this down a little bit right and I want to
explain kind of why we believe this and
really kind of what's going on because
everyone's kind of hearing about Agents
and the the need for data and and process
maturity but I want to explain it in as
simplest terms that I can to make sure
this point lands because this is
incredibly important to all of the folks
that are on the line here today that you
know want to start to invest in
AI generally speaking but particularly
agents here So let me let me break down
kind of this this idea of data management
with respect to AI and really data
management with respect to you know AI
agents
So first of all when I talk about you know
master data management for the purposes of
AI I'm not talking about simply how we
Govern and manage and really think about
just structured data Right like there's
this this misnomer in procurement that
that goes something like you know when we
talk about data management we're talking
about like a spend taxonomy or our
contracts repository or our master vendor
list Right that is important but that's
not really the the full story here When we
talk about data strategies for AI we're
really talking about a combination of
structured data Semi structured data and
unstructured data and it's really those
the the the the types of data that live in
that semi structured box and that
unstructured box that are really kind of
holding us back You can kind of think
about it this way if you want to wrap your
your head around this Think about any of
the work that you do today or the tasks or
activities that you know your employees do
today and then ask yourself you know what
data do I need or what data do my
employees need to actually move from point
A to point B in that activity or you know
in that task or as part of that workflow
I'd be willing to bet that there is a lot
of data that lives in that semistructured
that lives in that structured box right So
so a lot of folks are going to be looking
at you know Excelbased data or looking at
data that lives in you know Power BI or
Tableau you know stuff that's in a cell if
you will But I'd be willing to bet even
more money that most people are far more
reliant On semi structured and
unstructured data right So this would be
information that lives in like a SOP
document Or a process document or a policy
document or maybe on the unstructured side
it's information that you know lives in
like a Microsoft Teams chat or it lives in
your outlook or maybe it lives in your
brain after you've gotten off a Teams call
you know with a business partner about
requirements Right All of this sort of
data or all of this sort of information is
effectively a form of data that goes into
our brains as humans And gets processed
and it allows us to work through a task or
activity right So sensory input
information across structured semi
structured and unstructured data are
effectively the data inputs human beings
need to actually do work right Now the
insight here is that AI needs the exact
same thing If we want to deploy AI across
You know whatever use case or if we want
to deploy AI agents across any number of
use cases you know those models are going
to need the exact same thing They're going
to need that same sort of data to be
successful Now the unfortunate reality Is
that in procurement and really this is not
an indictment on procurement This is for
any functional area We are pretty bad at
managing semi structured and unstructured
data And I think this is partly because of
kind of how we grew up right We we've
always kind of focused on the structured
side but now the conversation really needs
to pivot to how do we manage and govern
that semi structured and that unstructured
data components And this is why you see a
lot of organizations investing in things
like business process mining You see
largely a lot of investments in very
advanced companies Into the areas of
understanding the ontology of their
business basically looking at it from the
perspective of do I fully understand the
mathematics that goes into decision making
and have I fully documented That
mathematics down on paper somewhere such
that I actually have a training database
for my AI use cases and my AI models and
my AI agents that I want to invest in to
learn from and to refer back to But again
you know most organizations aren't quite
there yet right So this is driving our
prediction that through the next couple of
years most companies aren't really at a
maturity level to get to this point Now if
you want to make improvements here The the
the place to start is really in
collaborating with your IT departments Now
every organization structured a little bit
differently right So so some of the larger
companies are you know maybe have some of
these resources in house within a sourcing
procurement team but by and large most
companies are going to need to collaborate
with their IT partners to make material
improvements here And so I want to just
kind of outline a bit of a
Quick journey if you will around kind of
what this looks like in practice Right so
let's say that you know you you want to
improve your quote unquote data readiness
you know for the purposes of AI right So
you have a list of use cases that you want
to deploy and you know you're looking at
this and saying well I need to you know
get better from a data perspective to make
sure that when I deploy these use cases
I'm realizing a a true ROI The first thing
that you you really want to do
Is you want to scrutinize all of the AI
use cases that you're assessing against
the current understanding of your data
maturity with respect to AI in the first
place So what this means is take a list of
your AI use cases that you're looking at
and actually ask yourself for each one of
these use cases do I fully understand Do I
fully understand all of the data points
that go into the decision logic and the
decisionmaking models of those use cases
across structured semistructured and
unstructured data Now this is a pass fail
you know step in the process Most of you
are going to quickly realize just how much
quote unquote tribal knowledge is holding
the organization together here because
you're going to find out that a maybe I
don't know all of the data points that go
into the decision logic of a particular
use case or b I know it but it's trapped
in someone's head and it's not documented
anywhere Right and so as you look at that
you have to either throw that use case out
if you don't know what data is going to
you know go into a use case or be you
have to develop a plan for documenting
that data somewhere Right the second thing
is you have to think about your governance
So if we look at the far the top right
hand side of the um The circle here you
know you know once you decide to move
forward with the use case you have to ask
yourself well how am I going to govern
that data Right Like what what does that
actually look like Are there ethical
concerns Are there compliance concerns Are
there data privacy concerns Right You have
to make sure that it's in full compliance
with the requirements of your larger
organization from a data management
perspective Right it's it's it's it's it's
not as simple as saying I know what data
goes into a use case You also have to ask
yourself can I even use that data in an AI
context And sometimes the answer to that
question is yes sometimes the answer to
that question is no Now let's assume we've
we've we've you know checked those two
boxes So we have some use cases where we
fully understand the data that goes into
them and we understand the governance
realities and we can still proceed At that
point we have to work with IT to prepare
those data pipelines Now this is something
that largely in my experience procurement
is not necessarily owning but this is
where IT is coming in and saying Okay how
can I actually connect these disparate
data sources across structured semi and
unstructured data to an AI model
And then you look at well how can I
enhance this Right How can I ensure the
accuracy of this This is the bottom left
Now you know the IT team is working on
basically refining and testing Right How
do I make sure this actually works in
practice You have this kind of virtuous
cycle that kind of unfolds Now I describe
that in you know three or four minutes
It's obviously a little bit more complex
than that but this is the general roadmap
That you're going to want to follow and I
would say from a data management
perspective focusing on step one and step
two there is incredibly critical to
success here
Now
It is my personal belief that we are going
to see progress being made here These
sorts of conversations this question
around kind of data management across semi
and unstructured data has been one of the
largest questions that we're getting
particularly from advanced companies
across the last eighteen months or so And
so I'm very confident that you're going to
see real material improvements broadly
across the marketplace in this space
across the next couple of years which is
what is driving kind of our our next
prediction here Which is you know as we
play out to the year twenty thirty now so
so kind of four years from now we are
going to see you know more and more agents
come online We're going to see more and
more AI capabilities you know really kind
of infiltrate all of business to include
sourcing and procurement and we believe
that by twenty thirty you're going to see
twenty percent Of procurement
professionals occupying new roles driven
by AI really requiring the CPO or broadly
kind of the procurement leader if you will
to adapt their talent strategies and
upskill their team members
Now let's break this one down right So
basically in the story we're saying okay
we need to focus on data It's a hard
challenge but it's not insurmountable But
as we start to overcome you know the
challenges there We're gonna have to pivot
to kind of the people component right And
this has been largely I think an ignored
conversation out there in the market It's
one that we're we're consciously trying to
change with our clientele because even
though AI is you know all about kind of
automating different use cases the human
being is still a a critical source of
competitive differentiation for our
organizations We can't ignore that So I
want to give you maybe a bit of a frame
of reference for How to think about kind
of this this human side here and how to
think about you know
adapting talent strategies and also
upskilling team members here To kind of
get into this I want to start with giving
everyone a bit of a frame of reference for
how we think about the role of both
you know the human and the AI models or
the AI agents Okay I'll say this when you
look at the work human beings do today It
can largely fit into one of two buckets
right So there is work that we do that I
would call patternbased work right So this
type of work follows rules it follows
norms it follows institutionalized ways of
working if you will Right There's
typically you know policies and procedures
and SOPs that exist to drive patternbased
work The lower you are in an organization
typically you're going to have more
patternbased work that you do But there's
another work type that we we are another
kind of bucket of work if you will that
human beings also you know support and
that is judgmentbased work This work
doesn't follow rules it doesn't follow
norms it doesn't follow patterns right It
requires a human being to to effectively
make a call So think you know responding
to COVID think um responding to
geopolitical you know uncertainty think
responding to you know all of the things
all of the Black Swan events that we seem
to be living through what feels like you
know every three to six months these days
Okay so we have these two work buckets We
have kind of pattern based work and
judgment based work Now we believe that as
we start to see AI come online as we start
to see agents infiltrate you know sourcing
and procurement to a greater degree than
they are today You're going to see that AI
is largely going to take over or at least
significantly augment That middle of the
page the patternbased work what I'm
calling here typical work right And it's
the reason is is it's very simple or the
rationale behind this is very simple where
we understand the mathematics behind
decision making So in effect where we know
what data goes into an activity and how
that data combines to produce an output
that we call the task That means in
essence that we have the training database
to train an AI model on how to go do
that thing how to go replicate that But
we do not see a world where the judgment
based portions of our work right So the
nonstandard the things I'm calling
nonstandard far left and far right hand
side on this page we do not see a world
where AI significantly augments or takes
over you know that that that sort of work
product And again the reason is very
simple there's no data to describe
decision making there Right So so for
example there's no training database that
you could have had um you know six years
to the day Right So six years ago to the
day we were all talking about COVID You
know there's no training database back
then to say here's the optimal response
strategy That required human intuition
human judgment human skills to kind of
navigate Right and so over time you're
going to see that AI agents will take over
that work which is pattern in nature
pattern based in nature and humans will
start to slowly gravitate towards more
judgment based work Right work that
requires true kind of human ingenuity if
you will to respond to Now one might
immediately conclude
from this framing That this means we need
less people we need less humans because
you might be thinking about this and
saying well there's so much that we do in
sourcing procurement today that is pattern
based in nature and to some extent you
know I I I agree with that but but in
to to to from another perspective I
actually kind of disagree with that and I
want to
maybe give you some talking points and
maybe a frame of reference and also maybe
let's just call it an argument As to why
we might actually need more people into
the future okay and it really boils down
to this idea that
As AI starts to impact the economy you
know more and more across the next few
years we're going to see two things happen
We're going to see the pace of business
rapidly accelerate and we're going to see
as a result the total volume of work
increase tremendously Okay so let me let
me kind of break this down
So prior to technology
Um there was a huge distance between what
we would call ideas and actions And if you
look at kind of like where work comes from
like like for example where does all the
stuff you do today actually come from or
where does all the stuff that your
employees do today actually come from Well
what happens is someone within your
organization has an idea and eventually
that idea needs to get actioned Right and
when those two things happen someone has
an idea and it gets actioned a work event
is born Right that's actually how work is
created Now prior to technology the
distance between ideas and action was
actually quite long Right like like
someone had to come up with an idea
Manually they had to turn that idea over
manually They had to you know critique
refine massage you know refine that idea
before it could get to an actionable state
manually And it took it took quite a long
time right And this is why
You know with the advent of you know the
internet computers it felt like the pace
of business has accelerated So if we look
at kind of where we're at today you know
with technology we have tools we have
platforms we have You know the ability to
basically truncate the distance between
ideas and actions I mean look at what
we're doing right now There's you know a
thousand of you on this webinar I'm
talking to you into this little microphone
over this thing we call the internet about
ideas We're refining those ideas in real
time I'm seeing questions come in about
those ideas We're massaging we're
tailoring we're tweaking those ideas in
kind of real time and that allows us to
get to an actionable place Right far
faster and so what's happened Well the
pace of business has accelerated and it's
actually increased the total amount of
work that we do I mean no one would say
that we do less work today than we did
thirty years ago
Because we have technology if anything
it's the opposite We do more work today
because we have technology because it
closes the distance between ideas and
actions Okay now with AI
It's going to be like pouring gasoline on
the fire right We not only have a tool
that can help us to refine polish and you
know turn our ideas over but we also have
a tool that can help us potentially come
up with new ideas in the first place right
And so again we're going to see this
paradigm shift We're going to see the pace
of business tremendously accelerate And
we're going to see the total volume of
work that we do as employees within
companies also increase In some ways I
would say we're living through this Right
I mean one of the things that you know
we've written a lot about across the last
few years is is this idea of cognitive
overload Like how do we shield our teams
from the the cognitive kind of
requirements of just like rapid change and
mass change at scale across the last few
years And so I would argue that that a lot
of us are actually kind of living through
this right now Right and so this is a long
way of saying I see an argument For this
notion that the increase in total volume
of work that we do actually keeps us at a
net neutral place or potentially even
increases the need for human beings And
the reason why is because as we encounter
new novel situations as the pace of
business continues to accelerate and as we
start to see new work requirements emerge
that is going to necessitate the need for
someone supporting more nonstandard and
judgmentbased work So while you may see a
net reduction in the middle of this page
across the coming years you're going to
see a net increase On the far lefthand
side and the far righthand side of this
page right there are simply more novel
situations more novel requirements that we
have to navigate as a functional area and
that is going to require human
intervention to overcome And so this is
why it's really really important for
everyone on this call
And really all of the business world to
really think about our talent strategy
here And there's a few things that I want
to hit on on this on this slide So first
of all we need to be thinking about
What new skill sets matter in a world
where humans are focused more on judgment
than they are on patternbased work
Because if you look at the skill sets and
the competencies that we largely have
across our teams today they enable
excellence at patternbased work for the
most part Right I'm not gonna I don't want
to paint the world in black and white
colors but for the most part most of the
skill sets we you know hire for and curate
and govern are related to patternbased
execution In a world where human beings
Start to focus more and more on judgment
Those skill sets become less important So
so the things on the right hand side where
you see the declining kind of column if
you will you know those sorts of skill
sets become less important over time So
things like deductive analysis process
execution you know financial acumen legal
acumen like those those things just matter
less in a world where we're doing more
judgment based work
Some new things become core right Things
like agility collaboration strategic
thinking you know influence and then on
the left hand side you have this whole
compendium of new skill sets That um you
know start to matter things like how do I
collaborate with an AI uh you know model
more effectively am I good at design
thinking What about ethical decision
making with respect to using AI models
right And so so the first thing that we
need to think about Is what's our plan for
upskilling here Right I mean do we do we
have a plan Do do we know what kind of
gaps um uh that we have with respect to
the the current competencies that are that
are kind of on our team Um the second
thing that I would say is you need to ask
yourself how are you going to actually
train for these new skill sets that are
emerging Um the reality is that we have a
broken
Kind of educational model around the world
So so let me kind of get a little bit
kind of philosophical here for for just a
moment If you look at how
our educational systems are set up all
across the world It is based on this
assumption that we send kids to school
starting at age you know between four and
six depending on kind of where you are at
in the world and then they stay in school
until anywhere between age seventeen
eighteen to twenty two twenty three again
depending on where you are at in the world
and how long you stay in in school But the
assumption is that you do that And kids
are going to come out on the other side
with the skill sets and with the knowledge
that they need to be successful for the
next you know forty to fifty years of
their career And if you really just step
back and think about that that's an
asinine proposition that is completely
disconnected to the speed at which the
world is moving today And so the question
that we need to be asking is also
Not it well it's it's not only what new
skill sets do we need but it's also where
are those skill sets going to be developed
right Because are we you know it's kind of
a hard hard thing to imagine sending
people back to school you know every five
to ten years to develop new skill sets So
are we going to you know fill that void
from a from an enterprise perspective Are
we going to partner with industry
associations Are we going to develop kind
of in house curriculum Like what is the
strategy there Because to be sure there's
going to be a new version of this slide in
ten years right So the things on the right
hand side maybe fall off the page the
things in the middle move to the right the
things on the left move to the middle and
there's a whole new set of things on the
left hand side of the page And so we need
to think about well how do we continuously
educate And that's something that you know
people have been talking about for years
but it's becoming a material
differentiator in today's economy just
given the pace of AI
The third and final thing that I'll say on
this slide is we also need to think about
how are we going to Enable effective
career progression
inside our organizations in a world that
is dominated by AI If you think about how
everyone on this call I mean just just
think think about your own experiences
here How did you get to where you are at
today I'm willing to bet you know most of
you would not say that they got to where
they're at in their career because they
sat through classroom based You know
trainings Most people were either given or
formed kind of a mentorship kind of
relationship with someone that then
afforded them stretch opportunities to
grow and develop Right And it's through
those stretch opportunities that allows us
to you know develop new skills and to you
know just just become you know more
dangerous in our profession if you will
The problem though with AI is that it's
creating a bit of a disincentive for real
and organic mentorship Okay I mean think
about it this way if you have a senior
employee
that has the ability to offload a portion
of their work To a junior level staff
member
or they can offload that work to an AI
model Who are you going to pick
Right one of those works twenty four seven
one of those can give you as many
potential responses to your questions or
to your prompts or to your requested
activities as many times as you want It
doesn't sleep You don't need to care about
how you you know
give it feedback
Who are you gonna pick Right you're
obviously going to pick the AI model And
so it's we're running headfirst into this
disincentive for career progression And so
one of the conversations that needs to be
asked and one of the conversations being
asked at the the the most advanced
companies we work with is How are we going
to protect
Judgmentbased or let me rephrase How are
we going to protect activities that
actually build judgmentbased skills for
the human being So even in instances where
we could deploy AI to do something how are
we going to govern those instances where
we say Yes AI could do this but this is
actually really critical for the human to
develop good skills that will allow them
to progress That is a fundamental question
That is an incredibly important question
that collectively we need to be answering
Otherwise we're going to run into real
problems years from now related to You
know skill set mismatches and we're going
to have a gap in kind of the career ladder
if you will Okay I'm doing a quick time
check I'm going to get to our third and
final prediction here which is another
build by the way on kind of the
the talent angle and then I'll I'll open
it up for Q A because I see a lot
of questions coming in So so our third
kind of prediction here
Is that again in the year twenty thirty
we'll see AI orchestrating procurement in
thirty percent of organizations So again
this idea that we are going to see real
progress across the coming years We're
going to overcome that data issue and in
in a span of you know four to five years
we're going to see real progress being
made on AI orchestration And when this
happens you know you're going to see tasks
being triaged To humans or AI agents based
on unique strengths in unique roles Okay
so let me kind of break this down here I
want to I want to just define real quick
what we mean by you know orchestration and
then I'll take you through a couple
implications and we'll open it up So first
of all I want to quickly define a multi
agent system platform for you all This is
something that I'm sure some of you have
seen in the vendor kind of communities in
maybe demos that you've seen of various
products or maybe you've seen this on the
roadmap of you know you know your own kind
of organization This is kind of a future
state everyone's kind of marching towards
But let me kind of break this down So in
the future we do imagine a world where
human beings largely interact with the
enterprise through AI systems first and
foremost So let's use a procurement
example here Let's say That we have a
human being that wants to buy something in
the future it's very likely that that
human actually begins the buying process
through interacting with what we call an
orchestrator agent Now this orchestration
agent will have been trained on things
like the procurement policy procurement
procedures maybe category strategies maybe
sourcing strategies supplier management
strategies Basically the entire context of
the organization's quote unquote
intelligence layer if you will it will
have been trained or at least connected to
that And the orchestrator has the
responsibilities of doing a couple things
The orchestrator first of all liaisons
with the human requester to understand
things like well what's your requirement
really like How many widgets do you need
Do you want lowest cost Do you want
highest quality What's your lead time So
on and so forth And then the second thing
is that the orchestrator is responsible
for basically kind of coordinating a
number of sub agents that are that exist
to basically operationalize that request
Right So in the in the example of say
A human needing to buy something the
researcher maybe takes that in and just
that that that request and then looks at
their sub agents that they have available
to them and says well maybe I need to call
upon the services of a sourcing agent
maybe a negotiations agent maybe a
contracting agent and then releases all of
the goal prompts and reviews the outputs
of all of those sub agents in the sequence
to basically action the request Now at the
end of this journey right it goes back to
the human This is where you get the kind
of the human in the loop if you will The
human can review what's happened maybe
engage the services of maybe a third party
agent to validate everything a compliance
agent and you have this kind of automated
kind of endtoend workflow This is
certainly where we think we see things
heading and we do believe that by the year
2030 we're going to see some organizations
deploy this at scale Okay now this is a
simple kind of buying journey Right this
is a very kind of narrowly cast example of
a kind of a simple buying journey What we
see happening more broadly speaking across
you know maybe more complex situations is
the need for the procurement leader
or the need for the chief procurement
officer really to orchestrate autonomous
procurement at scale Right and what this
means is to think about the interactions
of agents
alongside the interactions of say humans
Right so so we do not imagine a world
where Processes are only agents or only
humans It's really going to be a
combination of both right Where agents are
maybe passing the baton to
humans based on you know requirements at a
certain step of a process and then those
humans are passing it back to an agent to
take up the next step of the process And
what this requires us all to think about
is how do we update Kind of our operating
models our almost org design if you will
to reflect this new paradigm that we're
entering into So on the far lefthand side
you can see kind of these gray boxes These
are the inputs here right These are the
design tools that we need to think about
to really start to fully understand the
ontology of our business Right so
procurement leaders are going to have to
think about well how do we how do we know
what processes people are actually taking
on What's our model for those processes
How are we going to design workflows How
are we going to model out decisions Right
that gets fed into an LLM as part of this
broader intelligence layer In the blue the
light blue rather at the top of the page
you have these intelligence capabilities
Right these models need to be connected To
things like intelligent document
processing decision intelligence platforms
other sorts of AI or machine learning kind
of platforms and then You have these
endpoints at the bottom of the page where
the output of this autonomous
orchestration is being fed to various
sorts of individuals whether that's a
human whether that's a bot whether that's
an API connection somewhere whether that's
a future AI agent But I bring this slide
up and I know it's a bit of an eye
chart because there's a lot going on here
But I bring this slide up because as we
enter into this new paradigm of becoming
quote unquote AI first we need to become a
bit more sophisticated in how we think
about the procurement org chart Right AI
models AI agents bots largely speaking are
going to have to take their place
on the org chart and inside the operating
model alongside the human being for all of
this to work
Okay and this is a again this is a
conversation that we need to start having
Leaders are having right now to figure out
what is the optimal design design
decisions here Right I'll leave you with
one one last kind of insight before I open
this up to Q and A for the last fifteen
minutes and this is related to Another
kind of play on the talent or the human
side around how we need to reimagine
procurement's rolesthe human roles again
So I said a few minutes ago You know we're
going to see humans focus more and more on
judgmentbased activities I absolutely
stand by that and I believe that's true
But I'm going to take this a step further
today I think you're going to see
The emergence of many new and kind roles
to begin with You know so one of the
things that we've seen in the data and in
the research is that organizations that
are deploying AI models at scale today are
seeing productivity improvements at the
individual level But those productivity
improvements aren't scaling to the
enterprise wide level today and the reason
why we believe that's happening Is because
productivity is allowed to remain trapped
in individual role design and that needs
to change for us to really become AI first
And so what I mean by that is we need
to start looking at all of the roles that
we have in sourcing and procurement and we
need to start evaluating those roles based
on what percentage of activities and tasks
does that role take on today that is
innately human Or innately AI right So if
you look at the left hand side I'm talking
about the the evaluate roles kind of
circles there We need to take stock of
what roles do we have today and what
percentage of that work is actually a AI
you know native or or innately human in
nature right So pattern based or judgment
based work
Then we need to think about how do we
realign those tasks Right How do we take
all of those innately human tasks and
recombine them reconfigure them Maybe
create brand new roles Maybe we take the
portion of innately human work out of a
category manager a sourcing manager a
supplier manager and combine them into a
net new title Right and then how do we
peel out all of that innate AI work and
make sure that is you know given to the
agents It's given to the models It's given
to potentially copilot depending on what
scale we're looking at here
Then we reconstitute those roles in that
third step Right now we've separated out
Kind of these innately human roles these
innately AI roles and we need to update
all of this through our operating model on
the right hand side
What I just described to you on this page
is economic creative destruction in a
process Right this notion that new
technology comes online
That destroys some jobs that destroys some
requirements some activities but in that
process creates new ones This is that on a
slide right And this is what leaders are
focused on right now How do we transfer
productivity gains from the individual to
the enterprise through role redesign And
so this is the other conversation that is
happening right now in leading
organizations on the quest to get to that
twenty thirty date through that prediction
I just I just kind of outlined So with
that Tanya I'm going to pass it over to
you to maybe tee us up for the next
portion of our conversation here with the
Q and A and then we can go from there
Perfect Well thank you so much Ryan for
sharing your insights We have time to take
some questions now Please continue to
submit your questions and thoughts in the
ask a speaker box and remember to rate the
session So to submit your rating locate
the rate session link below the player A
box will open for you to select one to
five stars With five stars being the top
rating share your feedback on the insights
provided in the leave for the feedback box
and click send Before we get to the QA we
want to share some resources that Gartner
clients have access to If you are not
already a Gartner client please reach out
to your Gartner representative to learn
how you can advance your mission critical
priorities
Come join us at Gartner Conference here
from top Gartner experts in
thoughtprovoking breakout sessions and get
a personalized tour of the latest insights
and tools at the Gartner Showcase Discover
how Gartner can help you make smarter
faster decisions and achieve your mission
critical priorities Gartner clients be
sure to contact your client service
associate to register for the best event
for your role
Gartner clients have access to a suite of
benefits that you do not want to miss
Drive value across the business by arming
yourself with the latest business and
technology insights trends and
technologies shaping the future all
personalized for your role Connect with
your Gartner representative to learn more
Also please find a slide with recommended
research handselected by Ryan today If
you're not already a Gartner client please
reach out to your Gartner representative
on to how you can access material like
this and more
Additionally explore Gartner's sourcing
and procurement core for CPOs and
interactive Diagnostic that helps direct
and indirect
procurement leaders access function
effectiveness and advanced maturity Use
the CPO score to measure sourcing and
procurement maturity identify trends and
gaps and benchmark performance against
peerbased standards The tool delivers
actionable guidance and a clear pathway to
maturity enabling CPOs To prioritize
investments aligned with strategic
objectives and plan for both short and
longterm transformation visit gartnercom
to learn how Gartner can help a
procurement leader benchmark prioritize
and advance
Also follow us on social media and get
latest insights and trends Plus you can
download these resources from the bottom
of the page and get more Gartner insights
access additional resources and see
upcoming and ondemand Gartner webinars at
Gartnercomwebinars Please reach out to
your Gartner representative to take
advantage of these entitlements and
maximize your Gartner relationship With
that I'm going to quickly turn it over to
Ryan to address the questions now
Awesome Thank you Tanya Um so there's a
number of questions here I'm gonna
Us to get through as many as I possibly
can in the next ten minutes So first
question How do we manage employee fear
associated with AI investment This is a
this is a great question It's one that I
think Everyone should be asking if they're
not asking it already We do get this
question quite often So so to me it boils
down to two couple things One
it's it's similar to what I what I said a
few slides ago related to There's a strong
argument to be made that
There's a real need for more humans in a
world that's moving faster because there's
more judgmentbased work to go around and
so I think first of all explaining the
roadmap of where we see procurement going
is is a critical starting point kind of
painting that vision if you will for the
staff population because right now a lot
of the conversation is all about What are
we going to automate What are we going to
automate What are we going to automate
How much of the agentic AI models are
being used for direct material procurement
including strategic sourcing and discrete
manufacturing product bill of materials
Please share specific examples I have seen
use cases for several indirect procurement
And then the question kind of cuts off
there
How do I want to respond to this given the
short amount of time So
so we've seen AI being used broadly
speaking across direct and indirect
We I wouldn't say
The delineating difference or the extent
to which AI is being used is driven more
based off of data availability than it is
off of is this a direct spend or is this
an indirect spend In terms of specific
examples and use cases I don't know that
we necessarily have to get have the time
to kind of get into that today But off the
you know just an attempt to give you an
immediate response There the vast majority
of the use cases that we've that I would
say are quote unquote real that are
producing kind of tangible ROI Are
typically in the going to be in the
contract management space They are going
to be in the spend analytics space You've
seen some autonomous negotiations
technologies out there for tail spend type
requirements That's probably straddling
both the direct and indirect lines there
Um are going to be the kind of the places
that we start The the the more piloting
you know sorts of use cases are around
kind of the orchestration there are around
kind of full RFX automation there are
around kind of the end end kind of
autonomous sourcing if you
will um Another question here Should we
build or buy AI tools
Leaders today are taking a dual pronged
kind of approach to this There seems to be
Um uh uh within kind of advanced
organizations a mindset of let's let's
both try and build and buy to see kind of
where this shakes out I do think there's a
an argument to be made that says you know
if you build the AI models or if you build
the AI use cases yourself in collaboration
with the you know CIO or your IT teams
you are always going to have Better
contextual information to
feed those models Now the downside of that
is it you know sometimes costs more it's
more complicated to manage You know unless
you're set up to to really handle that it
can be hard to kind of govern you know the
the creation and management of an AI use
case to that scale like that Whereas you
know if you buy an AI tool sometimes you
get access to you know more market related
contextual knowledge So maybe it's not as
specific to your organization and how you
do business but maybe you tap into some
external sources which is valuable So
there's no one size fits all answer to
that I would say it depends on your goals
right So if it's kind of like a it's
similar to make versus buy right If you
view the use case as part of your
competitive differentiation as a firm to
me that's a signal to potentially think
about building a use case If you see it as
you know something that maybe
Maybe you would um you know outsource
traditionally then then I think it's it's
probably okay to to think about you know
buying but it's it's hard to give a
complete kind of response to that because
there's a lot of variables that go into
play but I would say think about what are
you trying to do is a competitive
differentiation through that use case or
is it more of an efficiency play if it's a
deficiency play it's probably going to be
okay to outsource um All right Next
question here I see negotiation in the
declining trend for new competency start
Please explain Yes this is a great one So
the rationale behind that and we went back
and forth on this for for for many many
months on where do we place that
The reason behind that is because
negotiation and to some extent is math
Right there has been plenty of
research written on how to negotiate You
have game theory you know a whole field
studying that You have
you know whole Harvard business you know
curriculums based around negotiation
strategy if you will The mathematics
around you know what negotiation is and
how to do it is largely
Is largely defined Now when I say math I
don't necessarily mean numbers necessarily
but I mean you know the the the relational
concepts between like what is happening
when negotiation takes place and because
that has been largely defined that means
that AI can do it We are already seeing
that we're seeing negotiation chatbots
come online We're seeing autonomous
negotiation solutions come online that can
actually negotiate with another human
being or if you want to take this a step
further can negotiate with another AI
agent
And and just think about the possibilities
of what happens when you have two models
negotiating against one another You
basically start to create the conditions
for dynamic contracts real time updates to
contracts infinite permutations of
negotiations that far exceed whatever the
human could do And so in a world where
that starts to happen we do believe that
that becomes a declining human skill set
It's not I'm not saying it's not important
um but it becomes something that Declines
in importance
Next
question In the autonomous procurement oh
no one just where to go
In the autonomous procurement
orchestration model what are the use cases
for human interaction The way that I would
answer this is the human interaction
belongs in the space where judgment is
required Right that's the simplest answer
that I can give you
It is it is in those places where the
organization deems we don't have a
mathematical equation defined well enough
to say this is the prescribed kind of a
RPA esque if you will way that we're going
to handle this A call needs to be made In
those situations the human has to be in a
loop
Um Albert asks How much process
standardization matters in training an AI
model to perform a task How to deal with
exceptions in the standard process How to
deal with nonstandardized process Um so a
couple questions in there So how much
standardization matters Um is really a
cost conversation at the end of the day So
you you can you know you can connect AI
models to you know incredibly unstructured
data sources and um it'll interpret it
right Like you for example you can connect
an AI model to YouTube and it can pull
information out of YouTube and you know
you you can action that right It's a very
unstructured data source and it can still
kind of infer like what's going on But the
thing we have to contend with is The token
economics of that right How much is it
going to cost the model from a token
perspective to effectively make meaning
out of the unstructured data right And and
and there's going to be a tipping point
where The cost of having a model sift
through unstructured data sources is so
great that using AI for that use case
doesn't make a whole lot of sense Like it
would be cheaper to employ a human to go
do that effectively Right and so so the
question of how much process
standardization matters I would say it
matters from the perspective of cost Right
the more standardized your processes are
the more semi or structured your data
sources become Therefore it's cheaper to
actually deploy the models How to deal
with exceptions Oh where'd the question go
Flying around how to deal with exceptions
in the standard process Again
that goes into kind of your business
process mining You want to have those
situational ambiguities really well
defined The if this then that's of a
process as defined as possible And then
how to deal with nonstandardized process
To me if it's truly a situation that
deserves a nonstandardized process that's
a situation that requires human
intervention human judgment Right and and
that that is an innately human task and so
I would say at this point in time really
don't even think about using AI for that
Now the exception to that is I do believe
there's a lot that we do today That is
pretty standardized in someone's mind It's
just not written down on paper anywhere
Right That's where the the whole tribal
knowledge kind of comes into play All
right I'm going to try and fly through or
try to get to kind of one other
question here Let me just
see Um
So Nick Nick asked Many of the ways that
newer professionals are hired and trained
is through completion of patternbased work
How do we set up a training pipeline in
the future to get new hires to have an
understanding of the basic structure of
what we do before they are asked to make
judgment calls
I pick this question because I think I
love this question This is so important to
me
There's this rhetoric out there that
basically says entry level work becomes
judgment based work Right Like you know in
an AI first paradigm we just eliminate
entry level roles and we just start them
at you know the judgment based level Again
I think that's an insane proposition For
the reasons Nick outlined right You need
pattern based like how you build judgment
is through the execution of pattern based
work right That's how you you know develop
wisdom That's how you develop good
judgment to make a call To me the answer
to this has to be
Us evaluating what tasks and activities
actually develop good judgment and then
protecting those for the human
A great case study and I'll leave everyone
with this a great case study in this is
what happened when the Da Vinci was
invented
So the Da Vinci is a surgical robot that
can help you know with like laparoscopic
surgeries Well when that came out some
hospital systems saw that the head surgeon
During surgery started to outsource
activities to the DaVinci in not the
surgical residents and it was very quickly
they started to realize if we don't
protect those surgical residents' ability
to actually participate in certain aspects
of the surgery we're going to run out of a
pipeline for head surgeons in a few years
Right and so so they basically started to
carve out and said Hey we know this robot
can do a portion of the surgery but we're
not going to let it because we need the
human to develop that skill Or really
develop good judgment through that skill
so that they can become the head surgeon
later right So with that I know we're at
time I want to be respectful of that Tanya
I'm going to pass it back over to you I
know there's dozens more questions that I
didn't quite get to Please reach out to
you know your account executive or Gartner
Rittlard We're happy to get to all of
these But Tanya I'm going to pass it back
over to you to wrap up
Perfect Thank you so much Ryan for sharing
such amazing insights And before you all
go just a quick reminder you can access
additional resources at the bottom of the
page Please read this session and share
feedback on the insights provided
So to submit your rating locate the rate
session link below the player A box will
open for you to select one to five stars
Please note that five stars is the top
rating Share your feedback on the insights
provided in the leave for the feedback box
and click send Alright with that I'd like
to thank our presenter and of course
whether you are new to Gartner or one of
our existing clients thank you for joining
us today I hope you all have a great day
Goodbye Ryan Polk Gartner procurement CPO
agentic AI supplier multitier