Okay Rajesh Kandaswamy Gartner CIO IT 2030
democratization North Star reskilling
Hello and welcome to this Gartner webinar
IT 2030 How CIOs Should Re Invent IT for
the AI Age
Your task is driving stronger performance
on your organization's missioncritical
priorities
To do that you need trusted guidance that
provides clarity not just information At
Gartner we deliver that clarity by
combining forwardlooking insights from our
twentyfive hundred experts with rigorous
proprietary research methodologies
Our perspective is uniquely informed by
our handson work with five hundred
thousand client interactions across every
major function geography industry and
sector
We don't just provide the business and
technology insights We work with you to
apply them equipping your team with
practical tools and expert guidance to
achieve your goals
So whether you are new to Gartner or one
of our existing clients
today you
will get actionable objective insights
through an inhuman intelligence to help
you move forward with confidence I'm
Robert your moderator for this session
Before we get started I have a few tips to
enhance your webinar experience
Here are rules of engagement for watching
this session We'll pause for a moment to
give you time to review them
Around the video player you'll find a
variety of ways to interact with the
session We encourage you to participate by
clicking the Ask a Speaker box to submit
your questions and thoughts about this
program
You can submit a question anonymously or
if you choose your name title and company
can be visible along with your question
Navigate to the bottom of the page to
download additional resources
About this program you can rate the
session and share feedback To submit your
rating locate the rate session link below
the player Boxes open up using the one to
five hearts Please note that five hearts
is the top rating
Share your feedback on the insights
provided in the leave for the feedback box
and then click send This
webinar is being recorded You can watch
this presentation again
Find more insights on demand at
gartnercomslashwebinars
Now I'd like to welcome Gartner's
distinguished vice president analyst
Rajesh Kandaswamy Rajesh thanks for
joining us and now I'll turn it over to
you
Thank you Robert Hello everyone Thank you
for taking some time to spend with us
IT 2030 This is our topic
CIOs and technology leaders worldwide are
all wondering
more than delivering AI for business
should they be reinventing IT itself for
the AI age
Some of you are already working on a plan
Some of you are considering and some of
you are asked by the board
To address this me and a few of my
colleagues started putting together
research at the end of last year
and since the time we have taken feedback
from many of you who have been gracious
with your input to shape this presentation
Let's jump right in
So
as we all know AI is a powerful force And
I think we can all agree that while there
are many different forces that can impact
IT and here are some geopolitics economic
activity and so there could be others that
impact IT I think we can all agree AI is
the fundamental powerful force that is
going to reshape IT
And when we talk to many of you we see
that there are three big areas why this
question becomes important
One is AIdriven efficiencies
We can all see that because of AI the
ability to build technology is getting
easier
It might not be as much as some people in
the media or in the tech industries
portrayed to be
But there is benefit
whether it's in building code or managing
IT
So based on that will the IT organization
in the future be smaller or bigger
Second
we all see increased interest from
business wanting to build their own
technology
We call it democratization
This used to have a negative connotation a
few years ago
with shadow IT I'm sure most of you are
familiar with shadow IT When the worry was
rampant technology use that is done
without guardrails in business ends up
impacting IT
But now democratization is on a forward
march No code agent builders wipe coding
These type of tools are enabling business
to build more
And the third one is
Because of the ability to use AI directly
or use AI to build code we have a new
question Should I increase my build mix
versus buy compared to before
I'll give an example A few months ago
a CIO of a large global bank asked me
Rajesh I have this big fat check that I am
about to sign for a large enterprise
software vendor
Hundreds of millions of dollars I'm not
sure if we should sign it Why
One
I don't know what all AI is going to
change
Second this vendor is telling everybody on
Wall Street that they are getting twenty
thirty percent efficiency because of AI
but I'm not seeing my bill go down twenty
thirty percent
And lastly I don't even use everything
that they're buying from them
We use only a part
So this is what I am thinking Rajesh She
said
Should I get a set of developers from my
team
and ask them to build parts of the
software
Using Claude Code or other you know coding
tools and then use it and then instead of
me maintaining it turn the whole thing to
open source
This was in September even before we saw
the market trash software stocks
So CIOs are grappling with these questions
How will impact the future of IT
So we looked deep into that and then what
we realized is that there are a set of
things that need to be considered This is
not a trivial exercise We all know how
hard transformation programs are that you
work on
So in this presentation we wanted to offer
you three things that are the outcome of
that research
The first is what is the future state that
you should aim for What is that North Star
We developed a few models We call them
archetypes to help you bring through that
Second
what is the level of reskilling or job
changes you will have to consider for
people in your team
And it's not just deciding on the level of
changes
What is the right pace for you
Some of you might want to be AI first and
go all in
but at the other extreme some of you want
to be really cautious That's
understandable based on the nature of the
industry
And third we will look into the
implication to the tech stack itself
So these are the three areas that we are
going to look into as part of this
presentation and we have much more
research on this
So now to look into the future state model
What we see is it's important to consider
three different factors
One
supply itself
Because of AIdriven efficiency we see that
more can be done with the same number of
people or less
Second
what is your business telling you about
demand in the future
Not just based on how business is today
but what are their aspirations for
business Will they be investing in new
markets Will they want to increase margin
improve customer service Based on that
what is the trajectory
And these two used to be somewhat standard
when we match demand and supply
But the third factor is very important now
democratization the ability of business to
build technology What is the appetite in
your business
So when you use these three factors and
then determine what are the models that
are possible we find there are four key
archetypes that are important for you to
consider and we offer you to them
So what you see on the left is the demand
supply and then the democratization Notice
supply has got two elements number of
people and the units of work being
delivered They are not exactly the same
The belief is because of AI you can
deliver more with the same number of
people or less but how much more it
depends on your appetite
The first archetype is what we call lean
IT
Here
the demand is more or less the same
but the expectation is IT can be more
efficient with AI and can the size of IT
can go somewhat smaller than it is today
There are organizations who to whom I
presented this that clearly say Yes you
know my CEO or my board expects me to be
lean IT or We are owned by a private
equity firm that is expecting us to
proceed that way
Some of you tell us that you are seeing
demand increase
but there is no appetite to increase
headcount in IT
Through AIdriven efficiencies you want to
match the demand
This is amplified IT
Some of you tell us that you know we are
seeing significant demand
But there is no appetite to increase IT
Yes we do want IT to deliver more
but we expect some of the demand to be
satisfied directly by business We call
this democratized IT
And some of you say that we are seeing
significant potential for technology
across
We want to build more In fact technology
is so critical we might reduce our buy
solutions and build somewhat more using AI
tools
So we want business to become more adept
in building technology but we also want to
invest in IT to deliver more technology
Because everybody builds we call it the
dual builder IT
So take a look at this
In terms of these four archetypes
this is not a progression
It is not unnecessarily one has to go from
one to the other
There might be a couple of places where
some might consider you know why we are
amplified We want to go to democratize
That's okay
Some might say we are democratized We want
to go to dual builder That's okay
But it's not a natural progression
Think about what do you think is the model
that suits you
and also think about what does your CEO
think the model that is needed for your
organization And how do you determine that
There are two factors to keep in mind
If the transformation that you expect to
do because of AI is fundamentally only in
technology
these two models are fine
But if the model has to address changes on
the business side as well
the other two modelsdemocratized and dual
buildercome to the fore
The other way to look at this also is
depends on how vital is technology to your
business
Everybody says technology is important
That's not the issue
But in some places
it's much much more important to be stable
not risk unnecessarily
Stability triumphs innovation in those
places We tend to see lean and amplified
IT
And in the middle this is where we expect
most of you to be
It is you are investing in technology to
make use of the opportunities
Which is common but then there is a subset
of you for whom technology is critical
What do I mean by that
In these companies
if a competitor or a new entrant
introduces a technologybased product and
that can impact you or your business
Then you fit in that category
Okay we expect most to be in the middle
but the idea is you identify what suits
you
As I mentioned earlier there is no
onesizefitsall and there is not really
only one good one Not everybody needs to
be dual builder
So think about your situation
And the most important thing is this
this is really important to pay attention
Is
all the work that we see now lot in the
IT departments is focused on how IT can do
better in the AI world
But we are dangerously underinvesting in
the planning that's required to take care
of the technology that is going to be
built outside technology outside the IT
department
So how do you go about this
Start with business have conversations
with them to determine whether the demand
is expected to be more
Work with your business partners to
determine what is the model that is
required
And what we are urging is while you are
investing in AI it is time to take a
deliberate step to determine what is the
future state model for you in IT
and set that as the North Star And that
will enable you to plan the rest of the IT
changes required for your organization to
thrive in AI age
So you've taken a look at this Now we
wanted to
get your view on this based on what I have
shared
these four archetypes Which of these
archetypes is closest to what you think
your organization will need in the future
Robert can we kick the poll on
Absolutely thank you so much Rajesh Our
poll is now open and we'd like to know
what you are thinking You should see the
poll now pop up right over the slides in
case you can't see the poll on your
screens Please refresh your browser window
once the poll is visible Simply select the
answer of your choice and click submit And
then once we close the poll you'll be able
to see the final results in the video
player And please continue to enter your
questions into the speaker box Rajesh
looks like we're getting a lot of votes
coming in now
Um I can read them out for you right now
It's um let me sorry three Let me about
forty three percent
Yeah So let me spend thirty seconds while
people are voting to read you know
explain the four archetypes again just to
refresh your mind as you vote Number one
is for situations when you expect the
demand to be more or less the same but you
want to get more done with less IT
resourceslean IT
Number two in amplified IT you expect some
more demand but there is no appetite to
increase IT's resources But you want to
deliver more and be more efficient
Number three is democratizing IT further
increase in demand but no increase in IT
resources but somewhat more capacity with
AI But business does some more work with
democratization
Number four is dual builder IT
Here is the highest level of demand and
the organization starts to work and think
like a tech company and building more
rather than buying There is capacity to
increase across the board
Hopefully all had a chance chance to vote
Robert is the vote stopping to trickle
down
Yeah it looks like it's it's kind of
slowing down right now I'll close it in
just a minute because you'll see some
votes still coming in But right now it is
looking like number three democratized IT
is in lead with about forty two percent
and second is number two Amplified IT with
thirty five percent The votes are now
really slowing down So I'm just going to
close the poll for everyone to see and
bring up those final results
And as you can see a three democratized IT
is at top with fortyone percent and then
amplified IT with thirtyfive
four dual builder is at ten percent and
then lean IT is at eight and then I don't
know is at bottom at six percent
Excellent
First thank you all for if you don't if
you don't mind showing the results for a
little bit So people can digest the
results So thank you all for participating
in the poll So there are certain things
that stand out One democratized IT being
number one with Amplified Not Too Far is
what we do see in our conversations as
well And so your output matches what we
are seeing
And then notice the democratization this
element of business building our own
technology
If that is the most prevalent one the
question becomes Are we spending enough
time and effort to really get ready for
that across enablement across governance
and the tools and all of that
And notice one more thing in the poll
It's only six percent said I don't know
So ninetyfour percent of you have some
idea about the future state Hopefully
that's aligned with your executives
So now the question is If you have a clear
idea of the future do you have a
deliberate plan to get there
and what are the things to put in place to
initiate that plan and progress over time
That's the thing to consider
So we can take the poll of Robert Thank
you all for participating again Now
let us look into the next area
Which is transforming the workforce itself
So we identify the North Star on the
workforce side There are few things to
keep in mind One
in the last year symposium we shared that
you know one fifth of the work is done
with some help of AI but you expect all
the IT work is going to use some AI in
the next few years
But how will that automation be What will
be the collaboration be
One of my colleagues Kabe and her team
worked really wonderful work in this area
to really identify how much human AI
collaboration is possible in different
areas of IT
And it's not simple just replacing They
use a fivepoint scale
At the lowest end of the scale is when you
are using AI on the site
If I'm a developer I am using an AI
chatbot on the site to generate snippets
of code I copy paste and use
But at the middle level is when I am using
AI for specific tasks The same developer
using AI to generate a set of test scripts
run test scripts generate documentation
That is middle level of automation and at
the highest level it is across the board
Now in the same instance in SDLC it is not
only in development but it's also in
design putting the code in testing and
testing etc
Now how much of this automation is
possible
and more importantly what is a speed
that's suitable for you
The speed for somebody in a
technologically advanced company is not
the same as somebody who is not
Be identified three levels of speed that
you can think about
One certain companies are very cautious
Caution is more paramount than innovation
Some companies are opportunistic
They take the opportunity when business is
investing in AI
to make any IT enhancements
And third are organizations that are AI
first they make deliberate and proactive
investments in IT
without aligning to business to get ready
for the AI age So think about what is
suitable for you
And when you think that what we see is
across the different areas within IT that
you see here
The level of automation that's possible
for you varies
If you are an AIfirst company the level of
automation that's possible for you can be
quite high in an area like software
development or an enterprise applications
but not an IT core
But notice the level of automation that's
possible in software engineering by 2030
Four point eight out of five
But it's not just automation There is a
level of reskilling that's required
In some areas it's significant software
engineering and data
And what we see is in some areas the
headcount actually trending
We get these questions But Rajesh won't AI
impact headcount in these areas But what
we see is in software engineering and
cybersecurity As of now based on the
technologies we see coming
The efficiencies that you gain while it
reduces the demand it also creates more
additional work that can be satisfied so
there is more demand
And as of now
CIOs across the board are experiencing
increased demand
But if you take a cautious approach
not AI first what appears in orange is
possible for you The level of automation
may not be as much as AI first but it's
still quite a bit
But notice one area one line cybersecurity
Even if you take a cautious approach you
will need to make a level of investment to
automate
Because you are not fully in control of
your destiny
it depends on bad actors trying to you
know do bad things to you So you need a
level of investment for automation
Otherwise it's hard to keep up
I know this is a busy slide My apologies
There is much more detail behind it We
understand that the transformation that
needs to occur at each of these levels is
immense
and so this covers that
So I just mentioned it In some areas there
is efficiency but there is also increased
demand Software engineering and
cybersecurity stand out
That is on the skills and the people side
But how do they work
This is an important element that's
emerging now
Tiny teams
And in the age before AI say whether it is
in ERP or mobile we used to have this
concept of big program teams
We knew what we wanted to achieve We knew
an instinct for the technology build a
large program achieve it ERP core banking
supply chain internetall of them were like
that
But AI is not like that
There is no clear instate in AI
Right Do we all know the instate in AI for
your organization For most of the people I
speak with they don't
But we all know which way to go Though
it's like kind of running in a race versus
running in one direction In either case
you need to train Either case you need
shoes Though in race you know the
destination but in some cases you don't
You still need these other things
So now
What organizations are doing is they are
building these small tiny teams in part of
AI without necessarily having a large
program team Let me give an example
A payroll company that I speak with
They get all these requests from their
customers On Wednesday they may get a
request for a payroll to be done over the
weekend
saying Hey Lucy did not work thirty hours
She worked fortytwo hours Can you make a
change This might come by email
And these emails are in different shapes
and forms
They used to have a human handling all
this
What they did was they built an AIbased
agent
The agent will process the email identify
what needs to be done extract the data
check internal systems validate it
check with the human whether that's the
right action and then make the change
Great
The customers are very happy because this
is faster and more efficient
The company is happy because it's cheaper
Now what did this company do is after that
they identified that this use case is not
repeatable everywhere
But the under there is an underlying
pattern
The pattern is about processing an email
extracting the data validating it checking
with the human
and then making the transaction
That's the same in customer service sales
enablement and other areas in the company
So they took that pattern and made it as a
platform
Supported by a very small team in
technology
that will work with
one or two people in business in different
areas and here is the kicker and will
proactively identify opportunities to make
that change
This is how we see AIbased transformation
today
find a new way to use AI where it used
to be done differently
Uncover the underlying pattern create a
platform and then go methodically apply it
everywhere Instead of one large team
that's what people are doing So the key is
to ensure there is an underlying platform
and supported by a tiny team
Might be one or two developers one or two
business people
but this is vital
That developer just doesn't say I will do
only developer They stretch themselves
They might do database work They might do
testing work
The business person might be one designing
the UI might be one using user acceptance
testing
So tiny teams are this emerging concept
This is not easy for most organizations to
absorb Many of you have been working to
simplify your teams Some of you rolled out
product teams That's great
But agents are not about products they are
about process So this is being needs to be
addressed
Let's play this movie out What happens if
tiny teams take hold more and more
Tiny teams operate mostly at the you know
the lower levels of the organization where
work actually gets done
And tiny teams have one or two people with
the help of AI to get stuff done right So
over time then you end up with a structure
like diamonds instead of pyramids
And then at the bottom the tiny teams use
AI to get work done whether in your
organization or in your service provider
A key question that comes to leaders is
Are we ready to make the change And second
when we think about this change if the
bottom level becomes narrow
How do we ensure we are grooming
tomorrow's leaders That's something to
think about
So the key takeaway in this is the this
area is this
We looked at the skill changes and that
needs to be addressed at a function you
know at a job level
Second it's not only about the skills it's
also about the tiny teams and thinking
what suits your organization
So we looked at that There is much more
detail on that area We have heat maps and
and whatnot to help you go through the
planning
Now the last one is on the technology
stack itself
Before I do this so let me ask a question
on democratization We spoke about
democratization business building software
So we wanted to run one more poll by you
Um Robert can you kick the poll Yeah
So we welcome your participation in this
poll
Democratization is the concept that I
mentioned is when business starts to build
more technology using web coding no code
agent builders and whatnot You have a
cloud cowork or something else In some
organizations you are actively promoting
this as a key strategy You might even have
platforms and guardrails in place Might
not be perfect but you have a clear
strategy
In some organizations you are
experimenting in some areas Either it
could be say within IT it could be in some
areas of business You might have just some
tools so you are encouraging it actively
but in some parts In some organizations
you are allowing it but with a clear
enterprise approach For instance
When Microsoft rolls out Microsoft Copilot
your people have ability to build agents
So you might have allowed it without a
clear strategy That's an example
Some organizations you're actively
limiting it not that you want to limit it
forever but right now you're being
cautious In some organizations you've been
worried about things like shadow IT and
the risk is so much or you might have been
burnt before with shadow IT so you're
actively discouraging it
Where do you fall in this Let's take our
30 seconds to answer that
Robert tell me when you have the numbers
are trickling down
Absolutely will do Again the poll should
have popped up on your screen So please
select your answer and then in
case you don't see it please refresh your
screen and that will be able to show up
And then click submit again when you have
your answer We'll close the poll in just a
moment for everyone to see the results
All right looks like still going pretty
strong there So and please continue to
keep your questions coming in for the
audience So I think we can
Close it out right about right about now
just for everyone to kind of take a look
and see
So here we go and we'll present the
results
And here you are So what we're seeing is
right now it's number two We are
encouraging encouraging it selectively in
specific areas thirty three percent and
then we're allowing it but without a clear
enterprise approach twenty four percent
That's tied With we are cautious and
limiting it due to risk and governance
concerns also twenty four percent and then
we are actively promoting it it's a key
strategy with platforms and guardrails in
place that sixteen percent and then the
last three percent is we are actively
discouraging it I'll hand it back over to
you
Yeah this is quite interesting As
you can see democratization is taking hold
Only three in three percent say they are
actively discouraging it This was not the
case with Shadow IT a few years ago I'm
sure we can all agree that if we had done
this poll five years ago the three percent
would have been much higher
So AI is definitely a change in mindset
about people wanting to use technology
And as you can see the you know the pretty
much every other option is about having
democratization in some fashion
and this supports this aspect of what you
all told us in the first call
With with support for like an amplified
and democratization so this is something
to really keep in mind Thank you all for
answering there and I notice that like you
know we haven't addressed any questions so
far since we are nearly at the halfway
mark Robert maybe I can address a few
questions before I spend time on the
technology section
Absolutely So question came in Sorry yeah
question came in about controlling risk A
question is like older days
Microsoft Access produced shadow IT
solutions How do you embrace AI but
control AI code creating further shadow IT
applications
Yeah
this is um
this this not an first There is not an
easy answer What we find is in this age
saying no it's not as much possible
because democratization is taking hold and
there is a new generation of technologies
and new generation There is more adapted
technology The question becomes How do you
balance governance and enablement at the
same time
One what we find is IT has got a
significant role compared to their role
during the age of shadow IT
AI most organizations or most people do
not fully have an exact understanding of
it It's not one technology and it's hard
to put a finger And this problem is worse
outside IT So first the part of the answer
is How do you control the risk First we
believe that IT needs to have an
enablement function to help business
achieve democratization How do you do that
Putting some clear controls Some
organizations have identified and curated
tools for specific people in business
and as they show proficiency can do more
Some organizations have created like you
know those type of no
code or like you know
agent sandboxes
where people can build In some places
where they start thinking about which
business capability that you want to
promote democratization more So the key
answer to you is How do you balance the
risk You identify where you can allow and
where you're going to benefit from
democratization while you can control risk
in doing it that way rather than only
looking at it as a tool enablement issue
That's what we see
Excellent Another question that came in
was actually similar to that What
advice would you have for the CIO whose
teams in the last three years
unfortunately earned the department of no
perception of the business You know what's
the most critical rotation in your view
Getting in in your view getting in front
of the AI challenge Did you sort of cover
that in that last answer Would you want to
expand specifically on this I can
specifically expand on this So this is
important I think
one it is vital to signal the changed
behavior Clearly the nature of the
question itself shows that there is an
intent to change I would follow that up
with specific signals For example maybe
you might want to consider providing a No
Code Agent Builder farm to a subset of
business people Maybe you simplify some
process One AI leader told me to build
that to create that behavior What he did
was he worked really hard to simplify the
vendor management process in their
organization He said it used to take eight
months Eight months
in the AI world Want to say for example
one of the most popular technologies is AI
agents He didn't even know about AI agents
this type of AI agents 15 months ago so
eight months is unacceptable He worked
hard to change from a assessment based
system to a rating based system
That showed business that you know the
people from IT really want to work with us
So you'd want to signal things like that
and then build more and more structure
into democratization
Hope that helps
Any other questions
That's big Do you have time for one more
or should we go Yeah we have a couple more
if we have time or we can Yeah we can
go forward Yeah this one may be too a
little bit broad But are there any Are
there differences by industry in what
you're seeing For which archetypes are
more prevalent
Yes the industry
so normally typically tends to be a very
very broad term There are some signals One
in organizations where there is higher
regulatory risk
The nature of dual builder might be
somewhat less other than in certain
pockets because
of the regulatory like you know compliance
needs that makes it a little harder to
achieve full dual builder There is some
democratization but not full dual builder
In some organais so that's in certain
industries like you know such as banking
in certain set of sectors of healthcare We
might we see but doesn't mean they fully
ignore it In some places they identify
certain areas for dual builder and
democratization within those organizations
and embrace it there with sufficient
guardrails
In some of well you know but the
interesting thing that we have observed is
Overall there is a shift towards more
democratization and dual builder compared
to a few years ago
Even say like I've had conversations with
certain public sector companies or highly
regulated healthcare companies that want
to look at like you know what are the
places in the organizations I can do a
democratize Maybe not full organization
maybe some parts That's what we are seeing
I can take one or two more Robert
more question Okay another question that
came in
I'd like to know what would be the ROI for
agentic AI in a highly regulated
environment The cost savings are no good
when there's a risk of the agent going
wrong
Yes rogue agent is a problem agent sprawl
is a problem orphaned agents are a problem
There are quite a few problems in that
area The
ROI is not necessarily only based on
whether the industry is regulated or not
It really depends on the strength of the
use case
There are some traps to avoid one trying
to automate a process that is inefficient
and lacks clarity or has bad data
The temptation is using agents to automate
a process that's inefficient Ironically
agents work better when the process has
clarity and the data is clean
I'll repeat that again
Well the belief is agents can solve
inefficient processes Ironically agents
work best when the process is clarity and
the data is clean
So that is one to keep in mind
Second is in many cases people try to take
process that exists today and think Can I
use agents to improve
But if the process doesn't have scale
then you don't get the benefit because of
AI agents
And if there are too many exceptions you
handle those exceptions by hard coding
again and again You reach a point of
diminishing returns very quickly
So the value might come in first
reengineering the process for agents not
humans
Or in some cases consolidating the process
against multiple units and doing it for
agents So you'd want to consider an
approach like that but then still look to
build an ROI business case factoring in
all the variable costs for agents and then
proceeding
Hope that helps
Um done with the questions Robert
A few more If you wanted to continue um
absolutely I'll take one more and then
we'll move I'll take one more and then
we'll move Okay one more All right
Next question is What happens if you do
not embrace democratization If you keep
the tech folks being the ones building the
solutions and business and the business
remains only users of the systems do you
fall so far behind in terms of velocity to
build capabilities
It depends on the industry It depends on
situation If you are in an industry where
you know the possibilities because of AI
and technology is high in business use
whether for your products and services or
for their everyday decision making or
working with the customer Then relying
only on technology people to build
technology solutions in this age of you
know cloud co work and white coding then
you might not be fully leveraging what's
possible in today's world
Definitely if that's the case you are
risking that And what are your competitors
doing
If they are embracing it or new startups
that can come and impact you are doing
that then yes there is risk
Thank you all for the question That's
wonderful Please keep the questions coming
We just have another five or so more
minutes and we'll have time at the end for
to address any additional questions as
well
So let me proceed So the last area is on
democratization the technology stack So we
all just saw that many of you are looking
at rolling democratization out
incausiously or putting processes in place
But overall democratization is of interest
to ninetyseven percent of you in some
fashion Only three percent said you're
actively discouraging it
So That means that we need to get ready
for that
Now
all of you have been working very hard to
make your technology stack AI ready
I get it it's not easy There is a whole
lot of things to do Data needs to be AI
ready Your apps need to be AI enhanced
Your middle bear has to be strong Your
infrastructure has to support the load
It's not easy
And some of you are just you know in the
process of doing it
But now I'm going to ask you to think
about
Do you have a plan for agent readiness
Your business might be coming up with
ideas for agents
and that's okay that's well and good But
as leaders of technology we urge you to
take a step back and think about what
portions of your IT stack
will offer the highest points of leverage
for you to roll out AI agents
What investments you need to make to get
them ready
And also are there programs that you
designed and planned
that were done before we all came to know
of AI agents but you're still continuing
to do that Maybe you can stop because you
don't want to transform once now based on
that old plan and then transform again
because you think agents are going to help
you
So that might be a place to save money
Now beyond that as we look to 2030
As all of you mentioned democratization in
some form what does it mean to your
technology stack
One enabling your technology stack to
support democratization when and where
Also providing business tools or sandboxes
or enablement or
governancewhat are the things necessary
That's worth that should be thought about
sooner than later That's where we see
your IT technology stack evolving by 2030
You will start moving from AI readiness to
agent readiness and democratization
readiness
This is not sequential
Some of you will have to do some of the
work sooner I mean most of you will have
to do some of the work sooner in stages
because your business demands it
So the question is how much
democratization does business want to You
know they want to move more from using it
to building it They do they want to also
like you know run it and secure it
As this drops what do some of you think
about
the risk that IT might have to handle with
Things are all well and good when things
go right
but what if things go wrong Who's going to
get the call I would bet it'll be somebody
in your organization for the most part
So that's something to really think about
What do we want business to own in this
area of democratization Having
conversations and laying out an approach
In some of you say that you know what
they are going to split and identify
places where every day democratization is
possible Certain set of things business
can do fine
Certain set of things we are going to hold
the line
Business can use it but we will build it
and run it Thank you very much
For example things like core banking in
banking and that's okay So those types of
models can lead on to like you know a dual
builder type of approach
Now
this we just spoke about this Another
element on the technology stack to
consider You know we started initially
with this example of the bank CIO who
wanted to build their own enterprise
software
Our answer to them is that it's not as
simple as AI replacing your software
Will AI and AI agents impact the
enterprise software build versus buy
landscape Absolutely
And you can be very strategic about it
So if you look at software some are highly
like you know business differentiating and
some are not You can talk to your business
partners to identify and you know whether
some software is highly technically
complex to build or not
If a software is simple
not very technically complex there is no
big business differentiation
then clearly that's a good candidate for
replacing with custom AI or even finding a
new AInative vendor who might be using AI
secret sauce or use agent coding to offer
you a different value proposition
In this case it's not worth investing too
much in embedded AI
But in some cases you may find that
actually this is a huge competitive
differentiator But that technology itself
is no complex Oh that's risky
What can you do to invest in that with AI
or like you know finding other vendors to
really strengthen your position so you are
not at risk
In some areas what you might see is it's
very complex for me to build an AI to like
you know to do The competitive
differentiation is not as much so I'm not
going to replace it I'm going to add more
AI to it And the very last is areas which
are really technically complex high
competitive differentiation What can you
do even more
With a strategic investment to exploit
that further
So if I remove the thing in the middle
what I would urge is look at your
technology stack
Where if you plot your key applications
where would they fall
And based on that you can start building a
nuanced strategy for your software stack
for 2030
So
we saw build versus buy I gave you that
example and I have been talking to a lot
of CIOs about this But I'm curious on your
take
Because of AIbased coding and the
capabilities that you're building and
because of other reasons whether you like
your relationship with your vendors are
you considering changing your posture for
2030 Do you expect more build or more buy
So here is the our last survey Thanks
Robert for kicking that in
So I the option one is you thinking you're
going to significantly do more by versus
build in the future
Option two is somewhat more by
Option three is now our build by mix is
going to be approximately the same and
then like you know leaning more on the
build angle
So think about your software landscape
primarily I'm not talking services this is
all about software and it's about the mix
It's the shift in the mix You might
increase both but the shift in the mix is
what we are trying to identify here
You can take a few you know another thirty
forty seconds
Absolutely thank you so much Rajesh Um yes
again poll is not open So click on your
response in your screen and then click
submit And then once the poll is closed
we'll display those results for everyone
to see And with the about ten minutes we
have left after this when we wrap up we
will be answering your questions
All right looks like polls results are
still coming in pretty strong right now So
won't close the poll just yet but we are
seeing number four somewhat more build in
the lead with about thirty five percent
and then followed up by no significant
change to our current mix now about twenty
seven percent there Let's give them twenty
twenty more seconds and let
me know when it tickles
Alright thanks Close the poll right now
Looks like we stopped There's results Yes
yeah So here we go
Yeah so it's a So yeah please go ahead
So looks like again somewhat more build
thirty six percent followed by no
significant change to our current mix at
twenty six and then somewhat more buy at
nineteen percent significantly more build
at ten percent and then
sorry significantly more build at ten
percent and a significantly more buy at
ten percent So Five in one tied at the
bottom there Yeah so as we can see it
leans more towards build The the
significantly more build and significantly
more buy cancel each other out The last
two options and around a quarter don't
expect a change So it's really among the
the rest of the fifty five It very much
skewed towards somewhat more build
compared to somewhat more buy That lines
with what we are seeing Of course building
more has its own set of challenges The
question is as you think about ID twenty
thirty If we think it's going to be more
built are you gearing up your
organizations with investment in software
engineering tools across SDLC with AI to
really uncover the efficiencies for you to
achieve that
And here we started identifying which
areas are you going to build more
and that areas could be areas of
competitive advantage for you not
commoditization And how are you managing
that How are you going to manage the shift
towards more build Is something to
consider Thank you for participating So if
we go back to the presentation so that's
the last part So what do we see when that
occurs
When that occurs you know if you look at
the slide this shows a simple
representation of how an application is
laid out right Or a technology solution
You got user interface at the top systems
of record at the bottom
So this is how it used to be in the
sense that most of the things we buy now
with AI we were doing little bit things at
the top
In fact one of the CIOs we spoke with
told us this and he's the CEO of one of
the largest companies in the world He said
they are fundamentally thinking about
giving away all the UI building to
business
IT won't manage it anymore
Business will directly take care of you I
knock yourself out We are good there
In AI agents we are starting to see this
line go down With AI agents now with
workflow and business largely could be
done with AI agents
So to what level for which business
capability that needs to be thought about
That'll help you when you say you're going
to do more building where and what is the
mix what business is going to do all that
So when you do that that leads on to new
questions Instead of buying an entire
package software top to bottom do you need
to start negotiating with your vendors to
buy headless applications or unpacked
software They're not going to like it I
can tell you right now they want to go
move up and up and sell you more AI agents
In fact
I'll give you a little anecdote I recently
asked a group of people in a conference
How many of you have not been approached
by your enterprise vendor to sell you AI
agents Show off hands Most of the people
raised hands But one person in the front
asked me Today
that is they have been reaching them so
much every day He's getting calls from
enterprise vendors
So our
suggestion is think about
signing longterm contracts especially in
places that can be impacted by AI
So this is our final thing
assess your IT stack readiness for AI
agent readiness and democratization
So as we come to the end
We looked at what is possible thinking
about an instate for IT because of AI We
looked at changes to your people the speed
and lastly the technology stack
Hopefully that enable you to think about
the importance of identifying a deliberate
Plan for IT to transform itself with AI
We share these archetypes Most of you have
an idea where you want to be
Do people in your organization share that
Is it worth talking to them to identifying
a deliberate plan so you can use that for
all the other decisions to come
And we believe that it will We believe
having a deliberate plan and transforming
IT is the single biggest thing that IT can
do to transform your business for the AI
era
Thank you for your time and making time
this morning or this evening wherever you
are We have another three four minutes for
the final questions I will turn it back to
Robert
Excellent Yes thank you so much Rajesh for
sharing your insights And to our audience
we will get to some Q and A now So
with a few minutes we have left maybe
answer a couple questions Um
First questions we have here Are there any
sorry are there emerging design or
architectural patterns that we can
leverage to improve agent output quality
to ensure we get the right get
it right in high risk use cases
There are evaluation patterns and
guardrails around those patterns It's not
as mature as the development areas in AI
agent We wish those those areas are much
more Unfortunately we can't get into the
details of the pattern We have published a
set of patterns around that So we consider
this there are some emerging not as mature
Next question Can you jump over from today
to agentready technology stack skipping
the AIready technology stack or even jump
to democratizationready stack
Yes and no In the sense first we would
urge you to start thinking about them
together but not fully finalizing But some
element of agent you know
Democratization is really you want to work
on now Now there are some elements of
which they depend on each other For
instance AI ready data you might still
want it for your agent readiness That's no
question But there are some elements that
can proceed independently For instance we
ask you to think about an agent readiness
audit which areas of your application
stack you really know what you want to get
ready For that you don't necessarily need
everything in the AI readiness stack to be
laid out So there is some dependency but
not all But we wouldn't think about it as
a purely sequential either
One last question maybe and then Yes time
horizon for the latest survey is pretty
short to fundamentally change mix
I think it's more about trends towards
well trend toward but to do all the
necessary things to shift the mix
contracts organizations reskilling etc At
an enterprise level will be tough
I think there will be pockets of major
disruption Do you see areas where you
think it will be more disruptive
And I think it'll be front office apps
maybe how we interact with SW
A front office depending on the nature of
the organization in very
customer focus customer brand focus it is
front office But there are organizations
that are very asset heavy say oil and gas
It's more in a back office It depends on
the organization Sorry we couldn't get to
all the questions Hopefully we were able
to address some Hopefully that helped We
have much more research available Thank
you for participating Let me turn it to
Robert
Excellent Yes thank you so much Rajesh I'm
sorry we couldn't get all your questions
but please reach out to your Gartner
representative with that Us and then we'll
try our best to get those answered Again
thank you so much to all of you for your
attendance Before you go we've included
some additional resources at the bottom of
the page far bottom of the page Quick
reminder this webinar is being recorded so
you can watch this presentation again And
get more great insights on demand at
Gartnercomwebinars And
lastly we ask you to please rate this
webinar below on the bottom right below
the video player To submit your rating
click the rate session below Click the
rate session button A box will open up You
select one to five hearts Please note that
five hearts is the top rating Share your
feedback on the insights provided and
leave for the feedback box And then click
send Again I'd like to thank our presenter
Rajesh and of course thank you for joining
us Have a great day Goodbye