Frances Karamouzis Gartner AI FinOps use
case CIO CFO
Hello and welcome to this Gartner webinar
Gartner's guide to identifying top AI use
cases funding and measuring value Your
task with driving stronger performance on
your organization's mission critical
priorities To do that you need trusted
guidance that provides clarity not just
information At Gartner we deliver that
clarity by combining forwardlooking
insights from our 2500 experts with
rigorous proprietary research
methodologies Our perspective is uniquely
informed by our handson work with five
hundred thousand client interactions
across every major function geography
industry and sector We don't just provide
the business and technology insights we
work with you to apply them equipping your
team with practical tools and expert
guidance to achieve your goals So whether
you're new to Gartner or one of our
existing clients today you'll get
actionable objective insights rooted in
human intelligence to help you move
forward with confidence I'm Alexis your
moderator for the session Before we get
started I have a few tips to help enhance
your webinar experience
Around the video player you'll find a
variety of ways to interact with the
session We encourage you to participate by
clicking the Ask the Speaker box to submit
your questions and thoughts throughout
this program You can either submit a
question anonymously or if you choose your
name title and company can be visible
along with your question Navigate to the
bottom of the page to download additional
resources Throughout the program you can
rate the session and share feedback To
submit your rating locate the rate session
link below the player A box will open for
you to select one to five hearts Please
note that five hearts is the top rating
Share your feedback on the insights
provided in the leave further feedback box
and click send This webinar is being
recorded You can watch this presentation
again and find more great insights on
demand at Gartnercomwebinars
And with that now I would like to welcome
Gartner Distinguished Vice President
Analyst Frances Karamouzis Fran thank you
for joining us and now I'll turn it over
to you
Thank you so much Alexis and greetings
everyone I'm excited to be with all of you
today to talk about Gartner's guide to
identifying top AI use cases funding and
measuring value So let's start with the
word top in the title There's no such
thing as top in an absolute sense Top or
the best is in the eye of the beholder I
would contend that each of you on this
call and your organizations likely have a
different set of criteria for what they
consider top On Gartnercom and in our
public research we use top when we're
measuring something objective like revenue
or headcount or a ranking The top use case
might be the one with the highest ROI but
if you're in public sector you don't
measure ROI You're unlike a private
enterprise
In 2025 haven't taken many of these calls
top use cases and or things that you know
sort of rose to the top as as highly
requested where clients were really
looking for cost savings of over 10
usually somewhere in the double digits and
they needed to be delivered within a time
horizon usually less than one fiscal year
And then of course we have in the title
measuring value And I'm going to get deep
into value creation and how you're going
to assess value creation because what also
happened in 2025 is lots of clients spent
a lot of time assessing the costs but
didn't actually assess the value before
they decided to fund the use cases and so
hence funding in the title So first
spending is going to continue unabated
It's still strong despite lots of
fluctuations and challenges across
different economies around the world and
different regions Spending on AI will
still remain strong So while there is cost
cutting going on you can take a look here
and see one of our data points 63 percent
of boards of directors rank investment in
technology and innovation as a top
strategy to navigate global uncertainty
Second item there in the middle top
leadership in the organization still has a
high level of confidence that betting on
AI is a primary driver for growth
Specifically 72
of CEOs are betting on AI
And finally if you look now in that last
column here the data that supports you
know some of my earlier points or what I
touched on on value it hasn't been
delivered Only 11 percent of CFOs have
been able to concretely measure ROI from
their AI investments
So this is actually showcasing lots of
different things here and I would bet that
if we were actually sitting here a year
ago and you were listening to a webinar
from Gartner these results would not be
all that different You would actually see
a lot of zealous enthusiasm about spending
on AI what AI can do and very very high
expectations
But what actually happened in 2025
what actually happened is there was a bit
of tunnel vision and that tunnel vision
was very laser focused on the productivity
of individual FTEs or employees What we
found in a lot of our research is that
productivity or individual FTE specific
productivity has not led to financial
value Namely we sort of talk about in
published time saved is not money saved
And here is one data point of the many I
probably have over a dozen slides on my
laptop that highlight this same concept
but I chose one here to kind of highlight
the point But we also have a lot of use
cases and case studies that showcase this
What you're seeing here on the screen is
on the xaxis is the number of hours saved
So sometimes you save an hour for someone
two hours three hours up to five hours But
then on the vertical axis you actually see
performance and this is from the
management teams reporting back whether
there was delivered Revenue or cost
savings in other words that the
performance that they were shooting for
get delivered and you can see this is a
pretty flat line here And this denominator
here of how many people we polled sixteen
hundred over sixteen hundred people So
this is a very consistent trend We
actually have data like this by function
And by industry that is all showcasing
that same thing The best way to describe
this is a quote from one of our clients
And this is a very common
sentiment that we're hearing But this
client talks about we have many examples
of what he's calling blue money and those
are productivity and efficiencies But
green money which is in form of direct
cost savings or revenue growth can only
come from critical business changes from
changing the process workflow Now we've
done a lot of work on green money and blue
money So let me just dive for a few
seconds on what we mean by this Blue money
is often money that has no direct PL
impact It doesn't flow on to a cost line
or a revenue line on your general ledger
and therefore does not flow to an income
statement Some examples of that is when
someone says Oh I increased the
productivity of X Y Z person This
individual FTE saved three hours or five
hours or We are increasing the net
promoter score or We increased customer
satisfaction Or the big one that I hear a
lot is cost avoidance we avoided spending
this money that we've done in the past or
reducing customer complaints or somehow
engaging employees increasing their AI
literacy their digital dexterity Now
Gartner isn't saying that these things are
not valuable What we're saying is these
things do not flow to a cost or revenue
line on a general ledger and therefore the
CFO isn't able to showcase them on an
earnings call What we mean by green money
is except the exact opposite of that where
the money does flow to a specific cost
line or revenue line and we have many
examples of that I'm going to show you
some case studies throughout this
presentation where you looked at things
like you've increased the sales conversion
rate you've increased cycle time you or
sorry decreased cycle time you've impacted
your inventory stock Or your total units
sold these are often KPIs that reside
within a very specific functional leader
who's on the hook for some of these
deliverables So Gartner has published and
if you're a Gartner client I put in the
link in the back of the session but also
here where we've spent a lot of time
saying if you've already started your use
cases And you didn't do a value assessment
So what you ended up with was a lot of
blue money as depicted in this
illustrative diagram on the left where You
came up with all these PowerPoint slides
It had bullet points that said we got this
value and that value but then when you
started trying to really showcase how they
flow it wasn't working My colleague
Gabriella Vogel has published these great
slides here and a lot of narrative behind
them of how do you start that journey of
trying to shift Blue money
to green money and she then has kind of
highlighted what is the return the
investment returns on that I won't go into
that detail but we wanted to showcase that
ongartnercom If you're a client or become
a client there's a lot of rich data and
research that you can access if you've
already started What I'm going to
highlight in this presentation is that you
need to change your behaviors and change
your approach and your financial rigor of
highlighting the
assessment of your use cases before you
actually fund them But we experienced and
showcased in a lot of our interviews what
we're calling the AI value gap
and that's really showcasing that
dichotomy where many people have invested
but haven't gotten the returns haven't
gotten the value creation And when we
start looking at the root cause of this
one of the big conclusions we came to is
that yes there's still elements of AI
technology and agentic technology that's
nascent But it hasn't often been the
failure of the technology It's much more
of the failure of these three items The
first one by far is Can your teams and
your functional leaders not only identify
but translate and communicate what really
are the sources of value creation In other
words how do you delineate value and how
do you make that transparent Instead
what's actually happened is many people
have just overindexed on what appears to
be the lowhanging fruit which is that
individual FTE productivity that I talked
about So this notion of distinguishing
value and making it transparent is where
the struggle really has been And that
ageold sort of like
you know friction Let's just say sometimes
between two different teams the IT team or
the AI team and the and the business team
not necessarily in alignment or talking
the same language That's actually been one
issue in AI That becomes compounded
because you also have data teams that are
very involved you also have security teams
that are very involved The second big root
cause is the financial rigor actually
doing a mathematical calculation Not just
a simple sort of as they say in the US
a back of the envelope calculation And
when I talk about governance in this slide
I'm talking about financial governance
enforcing whatever framework or rules that
you have for how are we going to vet how
are we going to prioritize and then how
are we going to decide what we're going to
fund based on a certain limits test And
I'll show you that in more detail But
what's actually happened is that's caused
a lot of lack of quantifying value at all
and just using slideware It's also
resulted in poor cost estimates and as we
moved from people doing
generative AI to agentic AI what's
actually happened is there's a whole
different way to calculate cost of agentic
and that's even harder than gen AI Gartner
has two different cost calculators one for
AI and generative AI and one for agentic
That's how complicated it is We had to
create a new cost calculator And then
there's an inconsistent funding approach
because lots of different teams have money
Not all the money is flowing like it used
to potentially where we decide what we're
going to fund and the money moves into the
budget of the CIO And then the CIO is
responsible for the projects and funding
the projects No that's not what's
happening If the head of sales the head of
marketing the head of supply chain the
head of finance if all of these different
people have their own budgets they are
going out and funding AI initiatives and
they're not using not everybody's using
the same consistent financial rigor And
then finally process change and that was
the big highlight of the quote from our
clients and many of our clients that are
talking about The shift is not really
about the failure of technology but the
fact that the ownership of the business
transition changing the process workflows
changing the metrics of the humans that do
those processes
engendering trust Looking at the operating
model all of those things are the things
that the business team is supposed to be
doing while the IT and the data team are
busy developing and testing the solutions
That's actually not happening So there's
been a fairly poor time horizon assessment
of when all of this stuff is going to come
to fruition and therefore we're going to
get the benefits So those are some of the
core root causes What has it led to in
2025 Clearly there has no been R or return
if you will in the ROI So there's been a
lot of investment and and very limited
results on value Likely over 80 percent of
clients are reporting that they invest a
lot and haven't gotten value creation That
needs to change in 2026
Now here is the data that supports all of
those things I highlighted We very
specifically and clearly asked What were
the primary reasons your organization did
not get financial value from your AI
investments And we allowed clients to
actually pick more than one because they
had more than one issue And you notice
selecting the right use cases was number
one on the list I'm actually going to
touch upon several of these I'm going to
touch on number one number two value
assessment number
four and number five are the big
highlights And you notice I skipped over
data Data is a very big issue for many
clients We actually have a team of 25
analysts at Gartner that solely focus on
data I am not one of them We do have
a number of presentations but data is
indeed one thing that can swing the costs
by very large margins The data cleanup the
data hygiene the data curation the storage
of the data integrating the dataso that's
a whole big topic and I don't mean to
overlook it But I want to focus on some of
the things that we can actually get done
with some of our Gartner frameworks our
Gartner guide to doing this And here is
more information that's highlighting the
very low confidence level in the people
that are looking at this in measuring the
benefits We specifically asked Where were
you And this is actually showcasing that
sixtythree percent of clients today either
have no or low confidence in their ability
to measure the benefits And that's why one
big thing I'm going to go over in this
session is a value calculator I'm going to
showcase both the value side and the cost
side So here I actually ask about the cost
as well This is a little bit better The
reason that this tends to
cause you know issues for clients is that
point that I talked about earlier where
calculating cost for AI and Gen AI is very
different than calculating cost for
agentic AI And so we do have a lot of
research coming up and we do have webinars
coming up on just the cost and value of a
Genetic AI So I'm not going to go into
that detail So I gave you a big backdrop
The real question is what do I do about it
To Alexis's point how do we make this
applied research How do we give you the
tools to make this work It starts with the
premise This whole rest of this
presentation The premise is that you and
your organization are going to implement a
rigorous repeatable enterprisewide
framework for funding AI Now enterprise
wide means that it's going to be
consistent amongst all those groups That
doesn't necessarily mean that only one
person approves everything You could have
multiple approaches to who's doing the
approving but they're using the same
rigorous repeatable framework And here's
where it starts We affectionately call
this the funding funnel You can name it
anything you like You can draw a different
graphic but the fundamental premise is
that there's no shortage of ideas There's
hundreds of ideas But we can only fund a
very small finite number of ideas and so
we need to consistently vet them Every
idea needs to be vetted We need to
prioritize them meaning juxtapose them
against each other especially if they're
disparate ideas If they're coming from a
lot of different groups you know one from
finance one from HR one from supply chain
There's a lot of different groups and
functions and they all want to submit
their ideas and they want to get them
funded
And then what you're going to do is you're
going to develop your Litmus test for your
enterprise And this is where I highlighted
in the very first slide your Litmus test
is got to be based on your business
strategy If you had a business strategy
and your CEO has come out and said the
three pillars of our strategy number one
is cost cutting number two is XYZ whatever
it happens to be you almost have to tag
any use case that you fund to one or more
of your business strategy pillars That has
been sorely lacking with many of our
clients but developing this litmus test is
a place where Gartner can help you But the
reality is is that this is not a one size
fits all This is very specific to each
organization and it needs to be again
reinforced every single time We can say
well this use case is an exception and
you need to then showcase Now there might
be some use cases that you say we're
willing to go in a longer time horizon Or
we're willing to get less ROI or less cost
cutting but they all need to fit into a
portfolio and they all need to be
transparent and communicated upfront What
is the value creation expected and
estimated and what is the associated cost
Not just the first year cost but the
recurring cost So here's how the framework
works There's two axes there's the
feasibility axis and the business value
axis What you're going to do is array all
those ideas and now you're going to go
through and mathematically calculate what
is the feasibility and what is the
business value creation expected You're
going to end up with and this is an
illustrative graphic is a very generic
example I put a few dots on there so that
you can start to recognize what a use case
might look like So customer profiling or
crossselling upselling These are obviously
very different in each industry and
they're not necessarily plotted the same
way for every client And I'll show you an
example If you look at asset predictive
maintenance I'm going to show you a couple
of examples of asset predictive
maintenance in four different industries
and they plotted them in different places
Why Because in some organizations if you
look at something like feasibility and we
go back to that point about data in one
organization they might have done a
phenomenal job over the last couple of
years in investing in their data
And therefore their feasibility score
might end up you know directionally being
on the higher end of the scale Then we
have a lot of other clients that say
Everybody wants data but no one wants to
pay for the data So we actually haven't
invested a lot in our data fabric over the
last five years and it's an enormous task
To clean up all our data to create the
metadata to understand how on a regular
basis we're going to curate the data So
their feasibility score which is one of
the variables feasibility might actually
be lower for the same exact use case
So if you go on Gartnercom and again we
invite you to be a client and to check
this out What we've done is we've taken
all the use cases that the Gartner
analysts have actually scored which I'm
going to show you in a second We have over
six hundred use cases in this tool It's an
interactive tool and what I did on the
right hand side of the screen is I took a
screenshot of and it doesn't all fit on
the screen of all the industries that you
can actually get these use cases and we've
done it by business function So if you
click on this link and it's also in the
recommended reading at the end you can
pick your industry and you can pick
multiple industries or multiple you know
functions Once you pick them so this is
what you'll often see in the left rail as
you look at this tool when you go on
garnercom
And it will generate something like this I
realize it's not visible I'm highlighting
to you the fact that even in this one
industry as an example for manufacturing
you could get product lifecycle
manufacturing you could get design and
engineering in manufacturing you could get
manufacturing operations And what is
actually these were created by the
analysts who are experts in these areas
and they've taken the top twenty or twenty
five use cases that they hear over and
over again in our client increase And the
analysts have scored them and that's what
they published And you could get that from
the interactive tool So you can create
your own By picking selectively the use
cases or you can download the entire one
This one is from software development and
testing I'm not going to go over these I
just want to showcase to you how rich this
is and how many different ones you can get
So I showed you the manufacturing Here's
two functions software and infrastructure
that are in IT and then of course here's
the HR function So you can see our HR team
has gone deep not just the overall HR but
into the different areas of talent
management talent acquisition learning So
there's lots and lots that you could do
What I did before this webinar is I went
to this screen to show you what it looks
like on Gartnercom and I typed in
predictive maintenance And as you can see
on the right hand side of the screen
you'll see four areas of predictive
maintenance I think there's a few more
down below but nevertheless you'll see one
of these is for governance government
sorry one is for transportation They're
for different industries So as you can see
when you doubleclick on it the screenshot
that you'll get is you'll actually see
predictive maintenance You see in the
upper left right below the words
predictive maintenance You see the three
expert analysts who actually did this work
You could actually see their value and
feasibility
waitings and some of their areas and then
what the score was and then you could even
further double click and actually read the
narrative of why they scored it And then
of course if you're a client you could
then you know actually request an inquiry
to speak to that analyst and you could you
know healthy debate with the analyst and
say I can't believe you scored preventive
maintenance like this or like that There's
no way that we can do it you know at
that level And so you can really get the
color commentary the insight of how you're
going to apply this work So yeah doing
that What I wanted to highlight as you
look at creating your matrix you can use
those resources You can add your own use
cases that might be very specific to your
organization to your industry to your
function But what I will highlight is that
there isn't one person who's doing this in
your organization It's actually a
multidisciplinary team sport There's
actually two teams that need to be
formulated to do this work The technology
or digital leaders I'll call them which
include people from IT people from data
people from security people from
Enterprise Risk and even people from
finance and procurement and HR The
procurement people are really important
because they are also going to get
involved because they should be tracking
the cost and the pricing of different
vendors So they need to inculcate that
variable and I can tell you in many areas
of both Gen AI and A Gentic AI that many
many vendors in the market have changed
their not just their price but changed the
schema of how they price
Three or four times in a given year
because for those of you who are following
the industry there are many vendors that
aren't making moneythey're not profitable
yetand so they're looking for their own
breakeven point So they're actually
changing the schemas So you actually have
to be really really proficient at
assembling the different disciplines to
score the feasibility And then on the
other hand you also need to get the
business teamsnot the IT teams not the
data teamsbut the business teams need to
score the vertical axis because they are
the ones that can tell you what's the
minimum scope and scale that we need to
get this value What are the specific KPIs
we need to focus on And while they're
doing this scoring They need to digest
kind of and understand in their hearts in
their minds and in their guts that
essentially the business people are
responsible For all of those things I
talked aboutchanging the workflow changing
the operating model changing the metrics
of the humans that do this work So while
the IT team the data team the security
team are working on developing the
solution testing the solution they're
responsible for the quality and the
workmanship and the ontime and onbudget
delivery of the solution and they're going
to tell you the time horizon The technical
risks and the cost of doing this in the
feasibility analysis and the business
people are really going to say What is it
going to take and creating that
transparency and that delineation of value
that I talked about earlier
So here I just took some of the
feasibility variables that you could use
and just showed them to you on a slide so
you can start to get a sense of what we're
talking about It's not just starting from
left to right in those blue boxes The
software maturity the platform maturity
the vendor ecosystemwhere are they In are
they a startup or what's actually
happening What are the skills the
intellectual property the methods the
processes that we have in our IT teams and
our data teams to deliver this solution
How feasible is that What's our level of
technical debt The AIready data Gartner
has an entire framework for what are the
18 variables that constitute AIready data
The security aspects compliance and
regulatory and then what is it really
going to take What's the feasibility of
governing this after it goes into
production Similarly you can now showcase
and array which feasibility factors you
want You can weight them and then of
course you'll score them And very
important you want to highlight that
auditorial of why you scored them a
certain way and then pass that on to the
team that's going to do the work and pass
it on to your lawyers so that every place
you scored a vendor or a specific area
pretty low The people who are managing the
project and responsible for executing they
understand that And if you have a vendor
that says No no no there's no way I'm a
five or a six on this category your lawyer
can actually tell them then you will have
no problem putting in a clause to manage
and meet or exceed that criteria in your
contract So there's a lot of good value
that you get from the process that you're
going to carry through all the way through
to execution
And then the same kind of thing here I
highlighted for you what are the bigger
variables that the business leaders are
going to look at They need to take these
variables and translate them into value So
they're going to look at things like
customer centricity They're going to look
at like what's the change in the business
process what is the change or the delta in
the talent Who do we need to upskill and
reskill from our humans What are going to
be the new metrics They need to look at
all of these things And in our value
calculator we connect these things to KPIs
that again go to a cost line or a revenue
line on your general ledger and therefore
on your P L
So for every single idea or use case that
you're looking at you're fundamentally
behind the scenes looking at assessing and
calculating the cost calculating the value
And if if you are a public company you're
sorry if you are a private entity and
you're listed on the stock exchange you
also want to likely calculate more
specifically ROI
and of course assess risk
And so we've done that We've taken all
these tools that I'm talking about And
this session isn't designed to go deep in
every single tool but we're looking at our
cost calculator and looking at our value
calculator What we did and this research
was led by my colleague Rita Salam and
included about 15 analysts myself and
others And you'll see the URL link on the
bottom Where we took the 15 most common
use cases and we actually calculated the
cost the initial cost the recurring cost
and we also calculated the value creation
over a threeyear period So Gartner uses
this more portfolio framework the Defend
Extend Up End which I'll explain in a few
minutes But essentially these are most
common things So when you open this
research you will get an Excel spreadsheet
with 15 tabs because there's 15 items here
So when you look at something like Gen AI
assisted customer support the one I'm
gonna I chose to kind of double click on
for this session you'll see two tabs one
is a buy and one is a build And what
you'll see in that spreadsheet is the
whole audit trail of how we got this
information I won't go through all of the
detail but the main things you'll see
highlighted in the spreadsheet are what I
Pulled out and showcased here You'll see
on the left here what is the initial first
year cost including everything not what
you're just gonna pay to the vendor but
what you're gonna pay for the rollout for
the training for the deployment for the
integration and all of that and then
what's the recurring cost In this case I
chose to show it by user per user We do
have the aggregate as well and then on the
on the far right You see the value side of
it and here it says per agent This
actually really means call center agent in
this case So this data a lot of this data
comes from real clients And what's
underneath it is the underlying KPIs that
we use and it'll show you the metrics in
the spreadsheet But we did this for all
these use cases and we've published the
low range the high range and just an easy
quick way that you could take that
information and showcase it in your
presentation to your leadership So you'll
see on the far right is the cumulative
cash flow cumulative sorry value line that
is in the blue and the cumulative cost
line that's in the orange and where the
break even point is So it's available for
every one of these but you'll notice that
the break even line is different for every
one of them And I also want to highlight
it's going to be different for you This is
not meant to just be copied This is meant
for you to learn because your use
case is going to be a little different
Your data is going to be a little
different Your KPI is going to be
different Your vendor that you might be
using is different from this particular
client But this is really trying to sort
of teach you how to do this and apply the
research And you'll notice in this example
this client actually chose to do this
where the cost line exceeds the value line
So they were not looking for specific ROI
They felt that they needed to get this
important insight into what's happening in
their sales cycle So this particular
leader had budget and was willing You know
to make this investment and when we were
having the conversation with this person
he said I'm going to bend that value line
It's not going to look like that in three
years We're going to really change our
processes and this AI solution is really
going to give us a different way of work
So it's quite interesting how people are
looking at this So there isn't again one
top or one single way To look at it but
I just wanted to just flip through all of
these to sort of show you that all of this
is available for you on Gartnercom And one
of the things we highlight is when you
sometimes what is the threshold of the
number of users that you need where maybe
a build makes more sense than a buy So
that's why in this particular case I
showed you the slides of the buy scenario
and the build scenario
So all of this now leads to case studies
So what I've been talking about so far are
use cases Those are the ideas and the
things that we are contemplating we might
do But Gartner also has a lot of case
studies of what clients actually did and
what we did is exactly the same thinking
same methodology that we wanted to follow
through where we took every single example
and said What How does this correlate to a
revenue growth area or a cost savings area
And so we found use cases or sorry case
studies for each one of these as as
examples And if you a reminder if you
followed this and you went on Gartner dot
com and you did the use cases you could do
the next part of the follow through which
is drill down and find a case study So you
say Well I'm thinking about this use case
Here's how I scored it and you can find on
Gartnercom a completed case study of that
example And of course since this isn't
legible since this is a screenshot I
actually created some nice slides for you
to show two three examples This is a cost
reduction example where and these were all
accumulated and documented and captured by
two of our data analytics analysts Aura
Papo sorry and also Carly Eodin and they
not only did these or captured these they
also behind the scenes said They did a
whole analysis on what is the right way to
simulate data Which technique of data
simulation do you need in order to achieve
these results And so they interviewed and
looked at these clients This particular
client was a logistics provider and they
were really focused on that last mile
effort and targeting a twenty percent
increase in ontime deliveries and capping
you know their fleet growth to under five
percent And you could see the outcomes
that they achieved I'm not going to go
through all of these in detail The reason
I included them in this deck is to
showcase for you that the outcomes all are
related to a KPI that flows to a general
ledger line item In this case most of them
are related to costs They're all about
cost drivers I also included one that is
much more about revenue growth This is a
multinational DIY and home improvement
goods company and they were targeting a
ten percent annual revenue
growth while maintaining you know a
balanced inventory and production You know
so to avoid you know sort of persistent
overstock And again if you look on the
right and you sort of see what they did
and what results they got all of these
case studies are on Gartner dot com that
you can dive you know deeper into And then
because I didn't want to exclude some of
people of our client base there are people
who don't only focus on growth and that
are public sector clients So this is an
example of a hospital Where they were
actually looking at this regional
healthcare network you know was looking at
average you know emergency department wait
times and so here they're dealing with a
very different KPI obviously related to
health and treatment and outcomes related
to patients and lives So it's a whole
other level of value But I just wanted to
showcase to you that value again or top or
best is really in the eye of the beholder
So when you look at all these use cases
they all need to link back to again
something that's going to grow your
revenue or drive cost savings And you know
when you ask or work with your business
people what you're going to find is they
know what the KPIs are The question is is
can they articulate what are the
underlying elements that delineate value
They might have 500 steps in a process Ah
fifty of them might be repeatable
commodity steps that everybody in your
industry does but there are targeted
things in those tasks and those processes
that actually are the makeorbreak or the
differentiator of value and so
When we do that as you assess your use
cases you're going to find that they fall
into
these three buckets And we use this as a
way to communicate and have a discussion
with the CFO the Chief Financial Officer
So you're going to have some use cases
that are going to be what we call the Fend
Those are use cases that give you
competitive parity They're going to give
you some marginal incremental gains
They're going to give you some micro
innovations These are often use cases that
sometimes don't have any ROI or very
little ROI A lot of the things in the
digital workplace or what we call at
Gartner everyday AI fall into this
category As a general rule and this is not
hard and fast but as a general rule
because these are not giving you ROI what
we often see is a small percentage Those
percentages on the bottom are the
percentage of your budget or the
percentage of the number of use cases that
you approve You might want to have a cap
on it at somewhere between five and
fifteen percent Let's just say ten percent
And in the middle you're going to have
things that are going to give you the
highest ROI They're going to either help
you grow in your market size your market
reach your revenue They're going to
decrease cost and therefore increase
profitability These are the ones that are
going to give you competitive advantage So
you might want to have a big lion share of
your use cases or eighty percent fall into
this category And then finally you might
have some gamechanging ones These are the
ones that often have that big time horizon
They often traverse one fiscal year Not
everybody has the wherewithal to do that
or the patience and so maybe they
introduce these later not in the first
round of their funding approvals But
depending on where you are you might want
to choose one or two of these and again a
small percentage of your budget somewhere
between five and fifteen percent If you
want to be a disruptor in your industry
we've seen clients have this number be at
fifty percent because they want to be AI
first AI everywhere They want to be the
bleeding edge in their organization We
find that most clients who are sort of
middle of the road and want to be more of
a fast follower they're really focused on
the ones that are not going to
disintermediate them
There is no right or wrong of these
percentages It's just important that in
your litmus test you have your caps of
where every time you approve a use case
you're tagging it to one of these to sort
of then report to your CFO how many use
cases and what percentage of your budget
you're using for them And the reason for
all of this Other than your CFO is you
need to manage these differently When you
think about these from a cost side the
defend ones you're gonna manage like a
cost center the extend ones you're gonna
manage like a profit center and the up end
ones you're gonna manage like a VC One in
twenty of these is gonna be successful so
very many of them are not gonna end up
going into production So you're doing this
for the value side which we sort of
highlight this way The value side of that
up end is the return on your future You're
doing all of these things to learn about
AGENTING to learn about algorithms to
learn how these tools and these
technologies behaving and what you need to
do So it's kind of return on your future
As opposed to starting from the left here
return on employee because these don't get
a lot of ROI We call it return on employee
because this is all about employee
empowerment You're often increasing the AI
literacy You're increasing the digital
dexterity of your folks You're empowering
the individual employees and in the middle
is where you're going to get the big ROI
So you want to think about it in this
portfolio and actually as you're approving
use cases you are accumulating your group
So now I leave you with what is different
about all of this In the old days what we
used to do is do design build run very
sequentially And in advance what we would
do is we would do a business case This old
school methodology is actually no longer
working It doesn't work in AI And if you
notice one difference is the business case
is kind of done once and you present it to
leadership and then leadership asks you
tons and tons of questions They really dig
deep they give you a hard time But then
once they approve it they then say Okay
you're off to the races Go go off and
design build run and do it What's really
happening in AI is a very different
approach It's dynamic it's iterative and
you actually have to go to management and
have some discussions maybe as many as
five times because what this actually
looking from starting from that bullseye
in the center P O B stands for proof of
value That is what you're doing in this
entire methodology that I highlighted
You're looking at each use case looking at
the feasibility you're looking at the
business value and on paper it actually
looks good So you're gonna fund it And it
meets your litmus test and your threshold
And then you're going to do a POC a proof
of concept At the end of that proof of
concept you are going to revisit your cost
calculation and revisit your value
creation assumptions because now you
learned from the POC And you're going to
make a nogo or a go or nogo decision Do
we move forward or do we actually table
this and we're not doing it because it's
going to be a black hole of spending or
it's not going to deliver the value that
we thought Um and you don't want to end up
in what our has now affectionately been
called POC purgatory We have clients who
started hundreds of POCs and they're all
sitting out there Very little has made it
into production In fact more than 60
percent have not made it into production
That's a big problem because you're just
spending spending spending and you're not
getting any results If you choose to move
forward you will now do a pilot And again
at the end of the pilot you've learned
more and what you're doing is revisiting
your cost revisiting your value creation
and then you're going to go forward and
execute Unfortunately you're still not
done because in AI in generative AI in
agentic AI you're not sure if you can
scale this So you're often going to go
through this usually twice two iterations
to feel really comfortable as you're doing
it And as you do it more and more this
becomes a high a very fast cycle time and
it becomes second nature So with that I
will highlight the final sort of words of
wisdom here that there's really two groups
of people doing this work the business
leaders who are responsible for the value
creation Um through AI and the behavior
changes of the humans and the decision
makers and how we're doing the work um
they're responsible for driving the
competitive advantage The technology
leaders are responsible again for the
workmanship the quality the ontime
delivery of the solutions So they're
responsible for the technology the data
the software the infrastructure and
operations and of course the cyber
safeguards I didn't talk a lot about
security in this session but obviously we
all know how excuse me how important that
is So they're managing the primary costs
and by extension many of the technology
risks So with that I will highlight that
value transparency is what's really
happening on the business side There's a
forced way of truly delineating value and
on the technology side we're seeing more
opacity You can no longer look at those
ten million lines of code You're doing
more of a black box So there's a lot more
work that needs to be done upfront So we
have some time for questions now There's
been a lot coming in Please keep them
coming in and ask the speaker box As a
reminder you can also rate this session at
the link below the player Five hearts is
the top rating or you can submit your
feedback on the Insights today in the
leave for their feedback box Before we get
to Q and A here are some resources to take
you deeper into the topic of AI
The insights you've heard today are just a
glimpse of the clear objective guidance
Gartner provides to help AI leaders drive
real business impact Gartner's solution
for AI leaders brings together
forwardlooking insights interactive tools
peer experiences and executivelevel
guidance from seasoned experts equipping
you to develop and execute an AI strategy
set strong foundations scale use cases
shape your tech stack and measure results
You'll also get rolespecific benchmarks
best practices and tailored insights Plus
ask Gartner our AIpowered tool to tap
trusted expertise instantly To learn more
follow the link on this slide or connect
with your Gartner representative on how we
can help your team accelerate its impact
Join us also at a Gartner conference to
hear from top experts network with fellow
AI leaders and get a personalized tour of
the latest insights and tools at the
Gartner Showcase Gartner clients please
connect with your client services
associate to find and register for the
best events for your role
And here you can find a slide with
recommended research that was hand
selected by Frances Karamouzis If you are
not yet a Gartner client please contact a
Gartner representative to find out how you
can access material like this and more
And make sure to follow us on social media
to get daily updates and insights to help
you lead a faster better smarter AI
organization
You can download these resources from the
bottom of the page Plus you can get more
Gartner insights access additional
resources and see upcoming and ondemand
webinars at gartnercomwebinars Please
reach out to your Gartner representative
to take advantage of these benefits and
maximize your Gartner relationship Okay
with all of that Fran I am going to hand
it back over to you to start answering
some of these questions Great fantastic So
let me start with the most voted question
here Someone asked Where do you see the
most value for AI in IT operations for the
business And I think there were nineteen
people who also said I have that same
question
Essentially first of all I'll just preface
my response by saying I'm not an
infrastructure and operations analyst One
of the slides that I showed you showed IT
Service Desk so that showed kind of where
our analysts are seeing the highest value
and highest feasibility ones Reading off
of that things like endpoint anomaly
responses on there intelligent
categorization all of those things
incidents What I will tell you is that in
my interviews with clients I have met a
handful of clients not a ton because I'm
not in infrastructure operations but I did
meet a client recently two weeks ago that
got their level one support almost To less
than ten humans doing it from hundreds and
so they have a lot of
AI that they implemented for primarily
level one and I do have another client
that I met that
reduced their costs to deliver certain
areasnot the entire infrastructure
operations but very specific areas of
infrastructure operations by 75 percent So
there are those are I think a smaller set
of clients at least that I've seen But
what I the reason I highlighted them is
because they are possible So I will tell
you that we have over a hundred analysts
in our infrastructure and operations group
because infrastructure and operations
still is over something like seventy
percent of a CIO's budget And therefore
that is a big bastion of area where lots
of savings cost savings are can be found
So hopefully that's a glimpse of an answer
But I would invite you especially if
you're a client or want to become a client
of Gartner the rich depth that we have in
our infrastructure and operations group
Ah second question was about ROI It's kind
of a long question I'm going to read the
primary sort of part of the question which
is Did we agonize over ROI for these
advances in technology the same way we're
agonizing over AI
It's sort of interesting because when you
talk to clients who've been in the
industry for 20 years One of the things
they talk about when and and you're using
the term agonized but one of the things
that they're talking about is when we used
to approve big projects like in the past
we did that big SAP initiative that was a
million or ten million or I've seen
initiatives that were over one hundred
million dollars all in
When you're paying for the product you're
paying for the consulting firm you're
paying for all of this stuff Um and you're
reorganizing your processes or the Oracle
project or the ServiceNow or the
Salesforce project Um they would take the
bigger projects and they would do this
kind of rigor The reality is why you need
to implement this for AI is because all of
the AI projects start to get into the
millions of dollars eventually not
hundreds of thousands but even for small
you know organizations whose scope is is
finite you don't understand how high the
numbers are getting For AI and that's why
when you end up with a CFO that has to
get on an earnings call and in the first
quarter identify we're doing all this
great stuff for our business using AI in
the next couple of quarters He she or they
actually have to showcase when are we
going to get this ROI what time frame and
how much did we get One of the projects
that we did in our team is we actually
downloaded the first six months of all the
earnings calls in twenty twenty five and
we're in the process of doing the rest
Where we were looking at in the earnings
calls where we were able to very directly
showcase a fairly good either correlation
or cause and effect of money you invest in
in AI and getting results And most
organizations are on the hook for that and
that's why we're in this place in terms of
agonizing over AI The other component to
that is AI is not a technology decision
only AI is a business decision that you're
making and that's the difference It's
traversed into many many areas far beyond
you know IT
The next question and just Alex just keep
me honest so we stay on time here But if
you reduce Headcount due to implementing
AI is that cost saving green money Great
question My next webinar by the way is all
about the connection between headcount and
savings and value creation So I'm going to
get deep into that But I don't want to
leave you hanging To answer this question
is it depends I talked to a client I've
talked to actually several banks and I
looked at the process called KYC which is
Know Your Customer In that process in many
large banks there are thousandsnot
hundredsbut thousands of people who touch
that process It could have over 500 steps
Some of them are compliance steps Others
are you know components of you know
qualifying the actual customer and things
like that Regardless every bank is
required to do them
or versions of them They're different It's
different in Europe as it is in Asia as it
is in the United States and Latin America
but nevertheless when you're talking about
thousands of people
If they eliminated or significantly
increased the productivity of ten of those
people or twenty of those or a hundred
I've seen people do that and not get green
money So the answer is it depends because
there are many many examples It's very
dependent on several things the complexity
of the process the scope of the process
It's also dependent on the tacit knowledge
the knowledge that's in people's heads
versus the explicit knowledge that's
documented and the exceptionbased
structures So sometimes getting rid of
these people helps but it doesn't change
the total marginal cost to deliver And if
you don't hit the marginal cost to deliver
number it's not going to flow to green
money So with that I think we're at time
Alexis why don't you close us out Thank
you everyone
All right Um So before everyone goes I
just want to send a quick reminder that
you can access additional resources at the
bottom of this page or as we noted go to
that ask a speaker chat ask the speaker
chat for the highlighted comment there for
the link to the tool that Frank was
talking about today Please rate this
session and share your feedback on the
insights provided And to submit your
rating click ahead here
To submit your rating you can click Rate
Session below the player A box will open
up for you to select one to five hearts
Please note that five hearts is the top
rating You can share your feedback on the
insights provided in the leave for the
feedback box and click Send All right with
that I want again thank Fran and of course
whether you're new to Gartner or an
existing client thank you so much for
joining us today Have a great day